<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing with OASIS Tables v3.0 20080202//EN" "journalpub-oasis3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table" dtd-version="3.0"><?xmltex \makeatother\@nolinetrue\makeatletter?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher">GMD</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Geoscientific Model Development</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">GMD</abbrev-journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta">Geosci. Model Dev.</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1991-9603</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>Copernicus Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Göttingen, Germany</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>

    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/gmd-9-1937-2016</article-id><title-group><article-title>Overview of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 6 (CMIP6)
experimental design and organization</article-title>
      </title-group><?xmltex \runningtitle{Overview of the CMIP6 experimental design and organization}?><?xmltex \runningauthor{V.~Eyring et al.}?>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" rid="aff1">
          <name><surname>Eyring</surname><given-names>Veronika</given-names></name>
          <email>veronika.eyring@dlr.de</email>
        <ext-link>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6887-4885</ext-link></contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no" rid="aff2">
          <name><surname>Bony</surname><given-names>Sandrine</given-names></name>
          
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no" rid="aff3">
          <name><surname>Meehl</surname><given-names>Gerald A.</given-names></name>
          
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no" rid="aff4">
          <name><surname>Senior</surname><given-names>Catherine A.</given-names></name>
          
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no" rid="aff5">
          <name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>Bjorn</given-names></name>
          
        <ext-link>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3795-0475</ext-link></contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no" rid="aff6">
          <name><surname>Stouffer</surname><given-names>Ronald J.</given-names></name>
          
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no" rid="aff7">
          <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Karl E.</given-names></name>
          
        <ext-link>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6491-2135</ext-link></contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Deutsches Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt (DLR), Institut für Physik der Atmosphäre, Oberpfaffenhofen, Germany</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Laboratoire de Météorologie Dynamique, Institut Pierre Simon Laplace (LMD/IPSL), CNRS,<?xmltex \hack{\newline}?> Université Pierre et Marie Curie, Paris, France</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), Boulder, CO, USA</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution>Met Office Hadley Centre, Exeter, UK</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>Max-Planck-Institute for Meteorology, Hamburg, Germany</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory/NOAA, Princeton, NJ, USA</institution>
        </aff>
        <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution>Program for Climate Model Diagnosis and Intercomparison (PCMDI),<?xmltex \hack{\newline}?> Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Livermore, CA, USA</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes><corresp id="corr1">Veronika Eyring (veronika.eyring@dlr.de)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date><day>26</day><month>May</month><year>2016</year></pub-date>
      
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>1937</fpage><lpage>1958</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>December</month><year>2015</year></date>
           <date date-type="rev-request"><day>14</day><month>December</month><year>2015</year></date>
           <date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>April</month><year>2016</year></date>
           <date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>April</month><year>2016</year></date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
<license license-type="open-access">
<license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
</license>
</permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016.html">This article is available from https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016.html</self-uri>
<self-uri xlink:href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016.pdf">The full text article is available as a PDF file from https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016.pdf</self-uri>


      <abstract>
    <p>By coordinating the design and distribution of global
climate model simulations of the past, current,  and future climate, the
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) has become one of the
foundational elements of climate science. However, the need to address an
ever-expanding range of scientific questions arising from more and more
research communities has made it necessary to revise the organization of
CMIP. After a long and wide community consultation, a new and more federated
structure has been put in place. It consists of three major elements: (1) a
handful of common experiments, the DECK (Diagnostic, Evaluation and
Characterization of Klima) and CMIP historical simulations (1850–near present) that will maintain continuity and help document basic
characteristics of models across different phases of CMIP; (2) common
standards, coordination, infrastructure, and documentation that will
facilitate the distribution of model outputs and the characterization of the
model ensemble; and (3) an ensemble of CMIP-Endorsed Model Intercomparison
Projects (MIPs) that will be specific to a particular phase of CMIP (now
CMIP6) and that will build on the DECK and CMIP historical simulations to
address a large range of specific questions and fill the scientific gaps of
the previous CMIP phases. The DECK and CMIP historical simulations, together
with the use of CMIP data standards, will be the entry cards for models
participating in CMIP. Participation in CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs by individual
modelling groups will be at their own discretion and will depend on their
scientific interests and priorities. With the Grand Science Challenges of
the World Climate Research Programme (WCRP) as its scientific backdrop,
CMIP6 will address three broad questions:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item>
      <p>How does the Earth system
respond to forcing?</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>What are the origins and consequences of
systematic model biases?</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>How can we assess future climate changes
given internal climate variability, predictability, and uncertainties in
scenarios?</p></list-item></list>
This CMIP6 overview paper presents the background and rationale
for the new structure of CMIP, provides a detailed description of the DECK
and CMIP6 historical simulations, and includes a brief introduction to the
21 CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs.</p>
  </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
<body>
      

      <?xmltex \hack{\newpage}?>
<sec id="Ch1.S1" sec-type="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) organized under the
auspices of the World Climate Research Programme's (WCRP) Working Group on
Coupled Modelling (WGCM) started 20 years ago as a comparison of a
handful of early global coupled climate models performing experiments using
atmosphere models coupled to a dynamic ocean, a simple land surface, and
thermodynamic sea ice (Meehl et al., 1997). It has since evolved
over five phases into a major international multi-model research activity
(Meehl et al., 2000, 2007; Taylor et al., 2012) that has
not only introduced a new era to climate science research but has also
become a central element of national and international assessments of
climate change (e.g. IPCC, 2013). An important part of
CMIP is to make the multi-model output publicly available in a
standardized format for analysis by the wider climate community and users.
The standardization of the model output in a specified format, and the
collection, archival, and access of the model output through the Earth
System Grid Federation (ESGF) data replication centres have facilitated
multi-model analyses.</p>
      <p>The objective of CMIP is to better understand past, present, and future
climate change arising from natural, unforced variability or in response to
changes in radiative forcings in a multi-model context. Its increasing
importance and scope is a tremendous success story, but this very success
poses challenges for all involved. Coordination of the project has become
more complex as CMIP includes more models with more processes all applied to
a wider range of questions. To meet this new interest and to address a wide
variety of science questions from more and more scientific research
communities, reflecting the expanding scope of comprehensive modelling in
climate science, has put pressure on CMIP to become larger and more
extensive. Consequently, there has been an explosion in the diversity and
volume of requested CMIP output from an increasing number of experiments
causing challenges for CMIP's technical infrastructure (Williams
et al., 2015). Cultural and organizational challenges also arise from the
tension between expectations that modelling centres deliver multiple model
experiments to CMIP yet at the same time advance basic research in climate
science.</p>
      <p>In response to these challenges, we have adopted a more federated structure
for the sixth phase of CMIP (i.e. CMIP6) and subsequent phases. Whereas
past phases of CMIP were usually described through a single overview paper,
reflecting a centralized and relatively compact CMIP structure, this GMD
special issue describes the new design and organization of CMIP, the suite
of experiments, and its forcings, in a series of invited contributions. In
this paper, we provide the overview and backdrop of the new CMIP structure
as well as the main scientific foci that CMIP6 will address. We begin by
describing the new organizational form for CMIP and the pressures that it
was designed to alleviate (Sect. 2). It also contains a description of a
small set of simulations for CMIP which are intended to be common to all
participating models (Sect. 3), details of which are provided in the
Appendix. We then present a brief overview of CMIP6 that serves as an
introduction to the other contributions to this special issue (Sect. 4),
and we close with a summary.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S2">
  <title>CMIP design – a more continuous and distributed organization</title>
      <p>In preparing for CMIP6, the CMIP Panel (the authors of this paper), which
traditionally has the responsibility for direct coordination and oversight
of CMIP, initiated a 2-year process of community consultation. This
consultation involved the modelling centres whose contributions form the
substance of CMIP as well as communities that rely on CMIP model output for
their work. Special meetings were organized to reflect on the successes of
CMIP5 as well as the scientific gaps that remain or have since emerged. The
consultation also sought input through a community survey, the scientific
results of which are described by Stouffer et al. (2015). Four
main issues related to the overall structure of CMIP were identified.</p>
      <p>First, we identified a growing appreciation of the scientific potential to
use results across different CMIP phases. Such approaches, however, require an
appropriate experimental design to facilitate the identification of an
ensemble of models with particular properties drawn from different phases of
CMIP (e.g. Rauser et al., 2014). At the same time, it was
recognized that an increasing number of Model Intercomparison Projects
(MIPs) were being organized independent of CMIP, the data structure and
output requirements were often inconsistent, and the relationship between
the models used in the various MIPs was often difficult to determine, in
which context measures to help establish continuity across MIPs or phases of
CMIP would also be welcome.</p>

      <?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><fig id="Ch1.F1" specific-use="star"><caption><p>CMIP evolution. CMIP will evolve but the DECK will provide
continuity across phases.</p></caption>
        <?xmltex \igopts{width=455.244094pt}?><graphic xlink:href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016-f01.png"/>

      </fig>

      <p>Second, the scope of CMIP was taxing the resources of modelling centres
making it impossible for many to consider contributing to all the proposed
experiments. By providing a better basis to help modelling centres decide
exactly which subset of experiments to perform, it was thought that it might
be possible to minimize fragmented participation in CMIP6. A more federated
experimental protocol could also encourage modelling centres to develop
intercomparison studies based on their own strategic goals.</p>
      <p>Third, some centres expressed the view that the punctuated structure of CMIP
had begun to distort the model development process. Defining a protocol that
allowed modelling centres to decouple their model development from the CMIP
schedule would offer additional flexibility, and perhaps encourage modelling
centres to finalize their models and submit some of their results sooner on
their own schedule.</p>
      <p>Fourth and finally, many groups expressed a desire for particular phases of
CMIP to be more than just a collection of MIPs, but rather to reflect the
strategic goals of the climate science community as, for instance,
articulated by WCRP. By focusing a particular phase of CMIP around specific
scientific issues, it was felt that the modelling resources could be more
effectively applied to those scientific questions that had matured to a
point where coordinated activities were expected to have substantial impact.</p>
      <p>A variety of mechanisms were proposed and intensely debated to address these
issues. The outcome of these discussions is embodied in the new CMIP
structure, which has three major components. First, the identification of a
handful of common experiments, the Diagnostic, Evaluation and
Characterization of Klima (DECK) experiments (<italic>klima</italic> is Greek for
“climate”), and CMIP historical simulations, which can be used to establish
model characteristics and serves as its entry card for participating in
one of CMIP's phases or in other MIPs organized between CMIP phases, as
depicted in Fig. 1. Second, common standards, coordination, infrastructure,
and documentation that facilitate the distribution of model outputs and the
characterization of the model ensemble, and third, the adoption of a more
federated structure, building on more autonomous CMIP-Endorsed MIPs.</p>

<?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><table-wrap id="Ch1.T1" specific-use="star"><caption><p>Main criteria for MIP endorsement as agreed with representatives
from the modelling groups and MIPs at the WGCM 18th Session in Grainau,
Germany in October 2014.</p></caption><oasis:table frame="topbot"><oasis:tgroup cols="2">
     <oasis:colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="left"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="justify" colwidth="398.338583pt"/>
     <oasis:thead>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">No.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">MIP endorsement criterion</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:thead>
     <oasis:tbody>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">1</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP and its experiments address at least one of the key science questions of CMIP6.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">2</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP demonstrates connectivity to the DECK experiments and the CMIP6 historical simulations.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">3</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP adopts the CMIP modelling infrastructure standards and conventions.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">4</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">All experiments are tiered, well defined, and useful in a multi-model context and do not overlap with other <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>CMIP6 experiments.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">5</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Unless a Tier 1 experiment differs only slightly from another well-established experiment, it must already have <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>been performed by more than one modelling group.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">6</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">A sufficient number of modelling centres (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 8) are committed to performing all of the MIP's Tier 1 experiments <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>and providing all the requested diagnostics needed to answer at least one of its science questions.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">7</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP presents an analysis plan describing how it will use all proposed experiments, any relevant observations, and specially requested model output to evaluate the models and address its science questions.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">8</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP has completed the MIP template questionnaire.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">9</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP contributes a paper on its experimental design to the GMD CMIP6 special issue.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">10</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">The MIP considers reporting on the results by co-authoring a paper with the modelling groups.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:tbody>
   </oasis:tgroup></oasis:table></table-wrap>

      <p>Realizing the idea of a particular phase of CMIP being centred on a
collection of more autonomous MIPs required the development of procedures
for soliciting and evaluating MIPs in light of the scientific focus chosen
for CMIP6. These procedures were developed and implemented by the CMIP
Panel. The responses to the CMIP5 survey helped inform a series of workshops
and resulted in a draft experiment design for CMIP6. This initial design for
CMIP6 was published in early 2014 (Meehl et al., 2014) and
was open for comments from the wider community until mid-September 2014. In
parallel to the open review of the design, the CMIP Panel distributed an
open call for proposals for MIPs in April 2014. These proposals were broadly
reviewed within WCRP with the goal to encourage and enhance synergies among
the different MIPs, to avoid overlapping experiments, to fill gaps, and to
help ensure that the WCRP Grand Science Challenges would be addressed.
Revised MIP proposals were requested and evaluated by the CMIP Panel in
summer 2015. The selection of MIPs was based on the CMIP Panel's evaluation
of ten endorsement criteria (Table 1). To ensure community engagement, an
important criterion was that enough modelling groups (at least eight) were
willing to perform all of the MIP's highest priority (Tier 1) experiments
and providing all the requested diagnostics needed to answer at least one of
its leading science questions. For each of the selected CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs
it turned out that at least ten modelling groups indicated their intent to
participate in Tier 1 experiments at least, thus attesting to the wide
appeal and level of science interest from the climate modelling community.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S3">
  <title>The DECK and CMIP historical simulations</title>
      <p>The DECK comprises four baseline experiments: (a) a historical Atmospheric
Model Intercomparison Project (<italic>amip</italic>) simulation, (b) a pre-industrial control
simulation (<italic>piControl</italic> or <italic>esm-piControl</italic>), (c) a simulation forced by an abrupt quadrupling of
CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (<italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2)</italic> and (d) a simulation forced by a 1 % yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
increase (<italic>1pctCO2</italic>). CMIP also includes a historical simulation (<italic>historical</italic> or <italic>esm-hist</italic>) that spans
the period of extensive instrumental temperature measurements from 1850 to
the present. In naming the experiments, we distinguish between simulations
with CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentrations calculated and anthropogenic sources of
CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> prescribed (<italic>esm-piControl</italic> and <italic>esm-hist</italic>) and simulations with prescribed CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
concentrations (all others). Hereafter, models that can calculate
atmospheric CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration and account for the fluxes of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
between the atmosphere, the ocean, and biosphere are referred to as Earth
System Models (ESMs).</p>
      <p>The DECK experiments are chosen (1) to provide continuity across past and
future phases of CMIP, (2) to evolve as little as possible over time, (3) to
be well established, and incorporate simulations that modelling centres
perform anyway as part of their own development cycle, and (4) to be
relatively independent of the forcings and scientific objectives of a
specific phase of CMIP. The four DECK experiments and the CMIP historical
simulations are well suited for quantifying and understanding important
climate change response characteristics. Modelling groups also commonly
perform simulations of the historical period, but reconstructions of the
external conditions imposed on historical runs (e.g. land-use changes)
continue to evolve significantly, influencing the simulated climate. In
order to distinguish among the historical simulations performed under
different phases of CMIP, the historical simulations are labelled with the
phase (e.g. “CMIP5 <italic>historical</italic>” or “CMIP6 <italic>historical</italic>”). A similar argument could be made to
exclude the AMIP experiments from the DECK. However, the AMIP experiments
are simpler, more routine, and the dominating role of sea surface
temperatures and the focus on recent decades means that for most purposes
AMIP experiments from different phases of CMIP are more likely to provide
the desired continuity.</p>
      <p>The persistence and consistency of the DECK will make it possible to track
changes in performance and response characteristics over future generations
of models and CMIP phases. Although the set of DECK experiments is not
expected to evolve much, additional experiments may become enough well
established as benchmarks (routinely run by modelling groups as they develop
new model versions) so that in the future they might be migrated into the
DECK. The common practice of including the DECK in model development efforts
means that models can contribute to CMIP without carrying out additional
computationally burdensome experiments. All of the DECK and the historical
simulations were included in the core set of experiments performed under
CMIP5 (Taylor et al., 2012), and all but the <italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> simulation were
included in even earlier CMIP phases.</p>
      <p>Under CMIP, credentials of the participating atmosphere–ocean general
circulation models (AOGCMs) and ESMs are established by performing the DECK
and CMIP historical simulations, so these experiments are required from all
models. Together these experiments document the mean climate and response
characteristics of models. They should be run for each model configuration
used in a CMIP-Endorsed MIP. A change in model configuration includes any
change that might affect its simulations other than noise expected from
different realizations. This would include, for example, a change in model
resolution, physical processes, or atmospheric chemistry treatment. If an
ESM is used in both CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-emission-driven mode and CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-concentration-driven
mode in subsequent CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs, then both emission-driven and concentration-driven
control, and historical simulations should be done and they will be identical in all
forcings except the treatment of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>The forcing data sets that will drive the DECK and CMIP6 historical
simulations are described separately in a series of invited contributions to
this special issue. These articles also include some discussion of
uncertainty in the data sets. The data will be provided by the respective
author teams and made publicly available through the ESGF using common
metadata and formats.</p>
      <p>The historical forcings are based as far as possible on observations and
cover the period 1850–2014. These include:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item>
      <p>emissions of short-lived species and long-lived greenhouse gases (GHGs),</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>GHG concentrations,</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>global gridded land-use forcing data sets,</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>solar forcing,</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>stratospheric aerosol data set (volcanoes),</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>AMIP sea surface temperatures (SSTs) and sea ice concentrations (SICs),</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>for simulations with prescribed aerosols, a new approach to prescribe
aerosols in terms of optical properties and fractional change in cloud
droplet effective radius to provide a more consistent representation of
aerosol forcing, and</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>for models without ozone chemistry, time-varying gridded ozone concentrations
and nitrogen deposition.</p></list-item></list>
Some models might require additional forcing data sets (e.g. black carbon on
snow or anthropogenic dust). Allowing model groups to use different
forcing<fn id="Ch1.Footn1"><p>Here, we distinguish between an applied input perturbation
(e.g. the imposed change in some model constituent, property, or boundary
condition), which we refer to somewhat generically as a “forcing”, and
radiative forcing, which can be precisely defined. Even if the forcings are
identical, the resulting radiative forcing depends on a model's radiation scheme
(among other factors) and will differ among models.</p></fn> data sets might better
sample uncertainty, but makes it more difficult to assess the uncertainty in
the response of models to the best estimate of the forcing, available to a
particular CMIP phase. To avoid conflating uncertainty in the response of
models to a given forcing, it is strongly preferred for models to be
integrated with the same forcing in the entry card historical simulations,
and for forcing uncertainty to be sampled in supplementary simulations that
are proposed as part of DAMIP. In any case it is important that all forcing
data sets are documented and are made available alongside the model output on
the ESGF. Likewise to the extent modelling centres simplify forcings, for
instance by regridding or smoothing in time or some other dimension, this
should also be documented.</p>
      <p>For the future scenarios selected by ScenarioMIP, forcings are provided by
the integrated assessment model (IAM) community for the period 2015–2100
(or until 2300 for the extended simulations). For atmospheric emissions and
concentrations as well as for land use, the forcings are harmonized across
IAMs and scenarios using a similar procedure as in CMIP5 (van Vuuren et
al., 2011). This procedure ensures consistency with historical forcing
data sets and between the different forcing categories. The selection of
scenarios and the main characteristics are described elsewhere in this
special issue, while the underlying IAM scenarios are described in a special issue in Global Environmental Change.</p>

<?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><table-wrap id="Ch1.T2" specific-use="star"><caption><p>Overview of DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations providing the
experiment short names, the CMIP6 labels, brief experiment descriptions, the
forcing methods, as well as the start and end year and minimum number of
years per experiment and its major purpose. The DECK and CMIP6 historical
simulation are used to characterize the CMIP model ensemble. Given resource
limitations, these entry card simulations for CMIP include only one ensemble
member per experiment. However, we strongly encourage model groups to submit
at least three ensemble members for the CMIP historical simulation as
requested in DAMIP. Large ensembles of AMIP simulations are also encouraged.
In the “forcing methods” column, “All” means “volcanic, solar, and
anthropogenic forcings”. All experiments are started on 1 January and end
on 31 December of the specified years.</p></caption><oasis:table frame="topbot"><?xmltex \begin{scaleboxenv}{.89}[.89]?><oasis:tgroup cols="8">
     <oasis:colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="justify" colwidth="56.905512pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="justify" colwidth="56.905512pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="justify" colwidth="85.358268pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="justify" colwidth="71.13189pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" align="justify" colwidth="28.452756pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" align="justify" colwidth="28.452756pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="7" colname="col7" align="justify" colwidth="42.679134pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="8" colname="col8" align="justify" colwidth="91.048819pt"/>
     <oasis:thead>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">Experiment short name</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">CMIP6 label</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Experiment description</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Forcing methods</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col5">Start year</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col6">End year</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col7">Minimum no. years <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>per <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>simulation</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col8">Major purpose</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:thead>
     <oasis:tbody>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry namest="col1" nameend="col8" align="left">DECK experiments </oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">AMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2"><italic>amip</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Observed SSTs <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>and SICs prescribed</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">All; CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concen- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>tration prescribed</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col5">1979</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col6">2014</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col7">36</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col8">Evaluation, variability</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">Pre-industrial control</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2"><italic>piControl</italic> or <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?> <italic>esm-piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Coupled atmosphere– <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>ocean pre-industrial <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>control</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>prescribed or <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>calculated</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col5">n/a</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col6">n/a</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col7">500</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col8">Evaluation, unforced <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>variability</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">Abrupt <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>quadrupling of <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concen- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>tration</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2"><italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> abruptly quadru- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>pled and then held <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>constant</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>prescribed</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col5">n/a</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col6">n/a</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col7">150</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col8">Climate sensitivity, <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>feedback, fast responses</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">1 % yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>concentration increase</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2"><italic>1pctCO2</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> prescribed to <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>increase at 1 % yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>prescribed</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col5">n/a</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col6">n/a</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col7">150</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col8">Climate sensitivity, <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>feedback, idealized <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>benchmark</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry namest="col1" nameend="col8" align="left">CMIP6 historical simulation </oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">Past <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 1.5 <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>centuries</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2"><italic>historical</italic> or <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?> <italic>esm-hist</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Simulation of the <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>recent past</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">All; CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concen- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>tration prescribed <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>or calculated</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col5">1850</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col6">2014</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col7">165</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col8">Evaluation</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:tbody>
   </oasis:tgroup><?xmltex \end{scaleboxenv}?></oasis:table></table-wrap>

      <p>An important gap identified in CMIP5, and in previous CMIP phases, was a
lack of careful quantification of the radiative forcings from the different
specified external forcing factors (e.g. GHGs, sulphate aerosols) in each
model (Stouffer et al., 2015). This has impaired attempts to
identify reasons for differences in model responses. The effective
radiative forcing or ERF component of the Radiative Forcing MIP (RFMIP)
includes fixed SST simulations to diagnose the forcing (RFMIP-lite),
which are further detailed in the corresponding contribution to this special issue. Although not included as part of the DECK, in recognition of this
deficiency in past phases of CMIP we strongly encourage all CMIP6 modelling
groups to participate in RFMIP-lite. The modest additional effort would
enable the radiative forcing to be characterized for both historic and
future scenarios across the model ensemble. Knowing this forcing would lead
to a step change in efforts to understand the spread of model responses for
CMIP6 and contribute greatly to answering one of CMIP6's science questions.</p>
      <p>An overview of the main characteristics of the DECK and CMIP6 historical
simulations appears in Table 2. Here we briefly describe these experiments.
Detailed specifications for the DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations are
provided in Appendix A and are summarized in Table A1.</p>
<sec id="Ch1.S3.SS1">
  <title>The DECK</title>
      <p>The AMIP and pre-industrial control simulations of the DECK provide
opportunities for evaluating the atmospheric model and the coupled system,
and in addition they establish a baseline for performing many of the CMIP6
experiments. Many experiments branch from, and are compared with, the
pre-industrial control. Similarly, a number of diagnostic atmospheric
experiments use AMIP as a control. The idealized CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-forced experiments
in the DECK (<italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> and <italic>1pctCO2</italic>),
despite their simplicity, can reveal fundamental forcing and feedback
response characteristics of models.</p>
      <p>For nearly 3  decades, AMIP simulations (Gates et al., 1999) have been routinely
relied on by modelling centres to help in the evaluation of the atmospheric
component of their models. In AMIP simulations, the SSTs and SICs are
prescribed based on observations. The idea is to analyse and evaluate the
atmospheric and land components of the climate system when they are
constrained by the observed ocean conditions. These simulations can help
identify which model errors originate in the atmosphere, land, or their
interactions, and they have proven useful in addressing a great variety of
questions pertaining to recent climate changes. The AMIP simulations
performed as part of the DECK cover at least the period from January 1979 to
December 2014. The end date will continue to evolve as the SSTs and SICs are
updated with new observations. Besides prescription of ocean conditions in
these simulations, realistic forcings are imposed that should be identical
to those applied in the CMIP historical simulations. Large ensembles of AMIP
simulations are encouraged as they can help to improve the signal-to-noise
ratio (Li et al., 2015).</p>
      <p>The remaining three experiments in the DECK are premised on the coupling of
the atmospheric and oceanic circulation. The pre-industrial control
simulation (<italic>piControl</italic> or <italic>esm-piControl)</italic> is performed under conditions chosen to be representative of
the period prior to the onset of large-scale industrialization, with 1850
being the reference year. Historically, the industrial revolution began in
the 18th century, and in nature the climate in 1850 was not stable as
it was already changing due to prior historical changes in radiative
forcings. In CMIP6, however, as in earlier CMIP phases, the control
simulation is an attempt to produce a stable quasi-equilibrium climate state
under 1850 conditions. When discussing and analysing historical and future
radiative forcings, it needs to be recognized that the radiative forcing in
1850 due to anthropogenic greenhouse gas increases alone was already around
0.25 W m<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> (Cubasch, 2013) although
aerosols might have offset that to some extent. In addition, there were
other pre-1850 secular changes, for example, in land use (Hurtt et al.,
2011), and as a result, global net annual emissions of carbon from land use
and land-use change already were responsible in 1850 for about 0.6 Pg C yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>
(Houghton, 2010). Under the assumptions of the control simulation,
however, there are no secular changes in forcing, so the concentrations
and/or sources of atmospheric constituents (e.g. GHGs and emissions of
short-lived species) as well as land use are held fixed, as are Earth's
orbital characteristics. Because of the absence of both naturally occurring
changes in forcing (e.g. volcanoes, orbital or solar changes) and
human-induced changes, the control simulation can be used to study the
unforced internal variability of the climate system.</p>
      <p>An initial climate spin-up portion of a control simulation, during which
the climate begins to come into balance with the forcing, is usually
performed. At the end of the spin-up period, the <italic>piControl</italic> starts. The
<italic>piControl</italic> serves as a baseline for experiments that branch from it. To account for
the effects of any residual drift, it is required that the <italic>piControl</italic> simulation
extends as far beyond the branching point as any experiment to which it will
be compared. Only then can residual climate drift in an experiment be
removed so that it is not misinterpreted as part of the model's forced
response. The recommended minimum length for the <italic>piControl</italic> is 500 years.</p>
      <p>The two DECK climate change experiments branch from some point in the 1850
control simulation and are designed to document basic aspects of the climate
system response to greenhouse gas forcing. In the first, the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
concentration is immediately and abruptly quadrupled from the global annual mean 1850 value that is used in <italic>piControl</italic>. This <italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> simulation has proven to be useful for characterizing the
radiative forcing that arises from an increase in atmospheric CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> as
well as changes that arise indirectly due to the warming. It can also be
used to estimate a model's equilibrium climate sensitivity (ECS,
Gregory et al., 2004). In the second, the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
concentration is increased gradually at a rate of 1 % per year. This
experiment has been performed in all phases of CMIP since CMIP2, and serves
as a consistent and useful benchmark for analysing model transient climate
response (TCR). The TCR takes into account the rate of ocean heat uptake
which governs the pace of all time-evolving climate change (e.g.
Murphy and Mitchell, 1995). In addition to the TCR, the
1 % CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> integration with ESMs that include explicit representation of
the carbon cycle allows the calculation of the transient climate response to
cumulative carbon emissions (TCRE), defined as the transient global average
surface temperature change per unit of accumulated CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> emissions (IPCC,
2013). Despite their simplicity, these experiments provide a surprising
amount of insight into the behaviour of models subject to more complex
forcing (e.g. Bony et al., 2013; Geoffroy et al., 2013).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S3.SS2">
  <title>CMIP historical simulations</title>
      <p>In addition to the DECK, CMIP requests models to simulate the historical
period, defined to begin in 1850 and extend to the near present. The CMIP
historical simulation and its CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-emission-driven counterpart,
<italic>esm-hist</italic>, branch from the <italic>piControl</italic> and <italic>esm-piControl</italic>, respectively (see details in Sect. A1.2). These simulations
are forced, based on observations, by evolving, externally imposed forcings
such as solar variability, volcanic aerosols, and changes in atmospheric
composition (GHGs and aerosols) caused by human activities. The CMIP
historical simulations provide rich opportunities to assess model ability to
simulate climate, including variability and century timescale trends (e.g. Flato et al., 2013). These
simulations can also be analysed to determine whether climate model forcing
and sensitivity are consistent with the observational record, which provides
opportunities to better bound the magnitude of aerosol forcing (e.g.
Stevens, 2015). In addition they, along with the control run, provide
the baseline simulations for performing formal detection and attribution
studies (e.g. Stott et al., 2006) which help uncover the causes of
forced climate change.</p>
      <p>As with performing control simulations, models that include representation of
the carbon cycle should normally perform two different CMIP historical
simulations: one with prescribed CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration and the other with
prescribed CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> emissions (accounting explicitly for fossil fuel
combustion). In the second, CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentrations are predicted by the
model. The treatment of other GHGs should be identical in both simulations.
Both types of simulation are useful in evaluating how realistically the
model represents the response of the carbon cycle anthropogenic CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
emissions, but the prescribed concentration simulation enables these more
complex models to be evaluated fairly against those models without
representation of carbon cycle processes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S3.SS3">
  <title>Common standards, infrastructure, and documentation</title>
      <p>A key to the success of CMIP and one of the motivations for incorporating a
wide variety of coordinated modelling activities under a single framework in
a specific phase of CMIP (now CMIP6) is the desire to reduce duplication of
effort, minimize operational and computational burdens, and establish common
practices in producing and analysing large amounts of model output. To
enable automated processing of output from dozens of different models, CMIP
has led the way in encouraging adoption of data standards (governing
structure and metadata) that facilitate development of software
infrastructure in support of coordinated modelling activities. The ESGF has
capitalized on this standardization to provide access to CMIP model output
hosted by institutions around the world. As the complexity of CMIP has
increased and as the potential use of model output expands beyond the
research community, the evolution of the climate modelling infrastructure
requires enhanced coordination. To help in this regard, the WGCM
Infrastructure Panel (WIP) was set up, and is now providing guidance on
requirements and establishing specifications for model output, model and
simulation documentation, and archival and delivery systems for CMIP6 data.
In parallel to the development of the CMIP6 experiment design, the ESGF
capabilities are being further extended and improved. In CMIP5, with over 1,000 different model/experiment combinations, a first attempt was also
made to capture structured metadata describing the models and the
simulations themselves. Based upon the Common Information Model (CIM,
Lawrence et al., 2012), tools were
provided to capture documentation of models and simulations. This effort is
now continuing under the banner of the international ES-DOC activity, which
establishes agreements on common Controlled Vocabularies (CVs) to describe models
and simulations. Modelling groups will be required to provide documentation following
a common template and adhering to the CVs. With the documentation recorded
uniformly across models, researchers will, for example, be able to use web-based
tools to determine differences in model versions and differences in forcing
and other conditions that affect each simulation. Further details on the CMIP6
infrastructure can be found in the WIP contribution to this special issue.</p>
      <p>A more routine benchmarking and evaluation of the models is envisaged to be
a central part of CMIP6. As noted above, one purpose of the DECK and CMIP
historical simulations is to provide a basis for documenting model
simulation characteristics. Towards that end an infrastructure is being
developed to allow analysis packages to be routinely executed whenever new
model experiments are contributed to the CMIP archive at the ESGF. These
efforts utilize observations served by the ESGF contributed from the
obs4MIPs (Ferraro et al., 2015; Teixeira et al., 2014) and ana4MIPs
projects. Examples of available tools that target routine evaluation in CMIP
include the PCMDI metrics software (Gleckler et al., 2016)
and the Earth System Model Evaluation Tool (ESMValTool, Eyring et al., 2016), which brings together established diagnostics such as those used in
the evaluation chapter of IPCC AR5 (Flato et al., 2013). The ESMValTool
also integrates other packages, such as the NCAR Climate Variability
Diagnostics Package (Phillips et al., 2014), or diagnostics
such as the cloud regime metric (Williams and Webb, 2009) developed
by the Cloud Feedback MIP (CFMIP) community. These tools can be used to
broadly and comprehensively characterize the performance of the wide variety
of models and model versions that will contribute to CMIP6. This evaluation
activity can, compared with CMIP5, more quickly inform users of model
output, as well as the modelling centres, of the strengths and weaknesses
of the simulations, including the extent to which long-standing model errors
remain evident in newer models. Building such a community-based capability
is not meant to replace how CMIP research is currently performed but rather
to complement it. These tools can also be used to compute derived variables
or indices alongside the ESGF, and their output could be provided back to
the distributed ESGF archive.</p>

      <?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><fig id="Ch1.F2"><caption><p>Schematic of the CMIP/CMIP6 experiment design. The inner ring and
surrounding white text involve standardized functions of all CMIP DECK
experiments and the CMIP6 historical simulation. The middle ring shows
science topics related specifically to CMIP6 that are addressed by the
CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs, with MIP topics shown in the outer ring. This framework
is superimposed on the scientific backdrop for CMIP6 which are the seven
WCRP Grand Science Challenges.</p></caption>
          <?xmltex \igopts{width=241.848425pt}?><graphic xlink:href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016-f02.png"/>

        </fig>

</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S4">
  <title>CMIP6</title>
<sec id="Ch1.S4.SS1">
  <title>Scientific focus of CMIP6</title>
      <p>In addition to the DECK and CMIP historical simulations, a number of
additional experiments will colour a specific phase of CMIP, now CMIP6.
These experiments are likely to change from one CMIP phase to the next. To
maximize the relevance and impact of CMIP6, it was decided to use the WCRP Grand
Science Challenges (GCs) as the scientific backdrop of the CMIP6
experimental design. By promoting research on critical science questions for
which specific gaps in knowledge have hindered progress so far, but for
which new opportunities and more focused efforts raise the possibility of
significant progress on the timescale of 5–10 years, these GCs constitute a
main component of the WCRP strategy to accelerate progress in climate
science (Brasseur and Carlson, 2015). They relate to
(1) advancing understanding of the role of clouds in the general atmospheric
circulation and climate sensitivity (Bony et al., 2015),
(2) assessing the response of the cryosphere to a warming climate and its
global consequences, (3) understanding the factors that control water
availability over land (Trenberth and Asrar, 2014), (4) assessing
climate extremes, what controls them, how they have changed in the past and
how they might change in the future, (5) understanding and predicting regional sea level change and its
coastal impacts, (6) improving near-term climate predictions, and (7) determining how biogeochemical cycles and feedback control greenhouse gas
concentrations and climate change.
<?xmltex \hack{\newpage}?>
These GCs will be using the full spectrum of observational, modelling and
analytical expertise across the WCRP, and in terms of modelling most GCs
will address their specific science questions through a hierarchy of
numerical models of different complexities. Global coupled models obviously
constitute an essential element of this hierarchy, and CMIP6 experiments
will play a prominent role across all GCs by helping to answer the following
three CMIP6 science questions: How does the Earth system respond to forcing?
What are the origins and consequences of systematic model biases? How can we
assess future climate change given internal climate variability, climate
predictability, and uncertainties in scenarios?</p>
      <p>These three questions will be at the centre of CMIP6. Science topics related specifically to CMIP6 will be addressed
through a range of CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs that are organized by the respective
communities and overseen by the CMIP Panel (Fig. 2). Through these different
MIPs and their connection to the GCs, the goal is to fill some of the main
scientific gaps of previous CMIP phases. This includes, in particular,
facilitating the identification and interpretation of model systematic
errors, improving the estimate of radiative forcings in past and future
climate change simulations, facilitating the identification of robust
climate responses to aerosol forcing during the historical period, better
accounting of the impact of short-term forcing agents and land use on
climate, better understanding the mechanisms of decadal climate variability,
along with many other issues not addressed satisfactorily in CMIP5
(Stouffer et al., 2015). In endorsing a number of these MIPs,
the CMIP Panel acted to minimize overlaps among the MIPs and to reduce the
burden on modelling groups, while maximizing the scientific complementarity
and synergy among the different MIPs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S4.SS2">
  <title>The CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs</title>
      <p>Close to 30 suggestions for CMIP6 MIPs have been received so far, of which 21 MIPs were
eventually endorsed and invited to participate (Table 3). Of those
not selected some were asked to work with other proposed MIPs with
overlapping science goals and objectives. Of the 21 CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs,
4 are diagnostic in nature, which means that they define and analyse
additional output, but do not require additional experiments. In the
remaining 17 MIPs, a total of around 190 experiments have been proposed
resulting in 40 000 model simulation years with around half of these in Tier 1.
The CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs show broad coverage and distribution across the
three CMIP6 science questions, and all are linked to the WCRP Grand Science
Challenges (Fig. 3).</p>

      <?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><fig id="Ch1.F3"><caption><p>Contributions of CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs to the three CMIP6 science
questions and the WCRP Grand Science Challenges. A filled circle indicates
highest priority and an open circle, second highest priority. Some of the
MIPs additionally contribute with lower priority to other CMIP6 science
questions or WCRP Grand Science Challenges.</p></caption>
          <?xmltex \igopts{width=241.848425pt}?><graphic xlink:href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016-f03.png"/>

        </fig>

<?xmltex \floatpos{p}?><table-wrap id="Ch1.T3" specific-use="star"><caption><p>List of CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs along with the long name of the MIP, the
primary goal(s) and the main CMIP6 science theme as displayed in Fig. 2. Each
of these MIPs is described in more detail in a separate contribution to this
special issue. MIPs marked with <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> are diagnostic MIPs.</p></caption><oasis:table frame="topbot"><oasis:tgroup cols="4">
     <oasis:colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="justify" colwidth="56.905512pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="justify" colwidth="71.13189pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="justify" colwidth="261.765354pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="justify" colwidth="56.905512pt"/>
     <oasis:thead>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">Short name of <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>MIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Long name of MIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Primary goal(s) in CMIP6</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Main CMIP6 <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>science theme</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:thead>
     <oasis:tbody>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">AerChemMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Aerosols and <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Chemistry Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Diagnosing forcings and feedback of tropospheric aerosols, tropospheric ozone precursors and the chemically reactive WMGHGs; (b) documenting and understanding past and future changes in the chemical composition of the atmosphere; (c) estimating the global-to-regional climate response from these changes.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Chemistry/ Aerosols</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">C<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>MIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Coupled Climate <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Carbon Cycle <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Understanding and quantifying future century-scale changes in the global carbon cycle and its feedback on the climate system, making the link between CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> emissions and climate change.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Carbon cycle</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">CFMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Cloud Feedback <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Improving assessments of cloud feedback via (a) improved understanding of cloud-climate feedback mechanisms and (b) better evaluation of clouds and cloud feedback in climate models. Also improving understanding of circulation, regional-scale precipitation, and non-linear changes.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Clouds/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Circulation</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">DAMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Detection and <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Attribution Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Estimating the contribution of external forcings to observed global and regional climate changes; (b) observationally constraining future climate change projections by scaling future GHG and other anthropogenic responses using regression coefficients derived for the historical period.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Characterizing <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>forcings</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">DCPP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Decadal Climate <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Prediction Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Predicting and understanding forced climate change and internal variability up to 10 years into the future through a coordinated set of hindcast experiments, targeted experiments to understand the physical processes, and the ongoing production of skilful decadal predictions.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Decadal <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>prediction</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">FAFMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Flux-Anomaly-Forced Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Explaining the model spread in climate projections of ocean climate change forced by CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> increase, especially regarding the geographical patterns and magnitude of sea level change, ocean heat uptake, and thermal expansion.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Ocean/Land/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Ice</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">GeoMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Geoengineering Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Assessing the climate system response (including on extreme events) to proposed radiation modification geoengineering schemes by evaluating their efficacies, benefits, and side effects.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Geoengineering</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">GMMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Global Monsoons <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Improving understanding of physical processes in global monsoons system; (b) better simulating the mean state, interannual variability, and long-term changes of global monsoons.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Regional phenomena</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">HighResMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">High-Resolution <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Assessing the robustness of improvements in the representation of important climate processes with weather-resolving global model resolutions (<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 25 km or finer), within a simplified framework using the physical climate system only with constrained aerosol forcing.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Regional phenomena</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">ISMIP6</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Ice Sheet Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project for CMIP6</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Improving confidence in projections of the sea level rise associated with mass loss from the ice sheets of Greenland and Antarctica.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Ocean/Land/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Ice</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">LS3MIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Land Surface, <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Snow and Soil <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Moisture</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Providing a comprehensive assessment of land surface, snow, and soil moisture-climate feedback, and diagnosing systematic biases in the land modules of current ESMs using constrained land-module-only experiments.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Ocean/Land/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Ice</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">LUMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Land-Use Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Quantifying the effects of land use on climate and biogeochemical cycling (past–future), and assessing the potential for alternative land management strategies to mitigate climate change.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Land use</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:tbody>
   </oasis:tgroup></oasis:table></table-wrap>

<?xmltex \hack{\addtocounter{table}{-1}}?><?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><table-wrap id="Ch1.T4" specific-use="star"><caption><p>Continued.</p></caption><oasis:table frame="topbot"><oasis:tgroup cols="4">
     <oasis:colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="justify" colwidth="56.905512pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="justify" colwidth="71.13189pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="justify" colwidth="261.765354pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="justify" colwidth="56.905512pt"/>
     <oasis:thead>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">OMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Ocean Model In- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>tercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Providing a framework for evaluating, understanding, and improving ocean, sea ice, and biogeochemical, including inert tracers, components of climate and Earth system models contributing to CMIP6. Protocols are provided to perform coordinated ocean/sea ice/tracer/biogeochemistry simulations forced with common atmospheric data sets.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Ocean/Land/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Ice</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:thead>
     <oasis:tbody>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">PMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Paleoclimate Mod- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>elling Intercompar- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>ison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Analysing the response to forcings and major feedback for past climates outside the range of recent variability; (b) assessing the credibility of climate models used for future climate projections.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Paleo</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">RFMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Radiative Forcing <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Characterizing the global and regional effective radiative forcing for each model for historical and 4<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> simulations; (b) assessing the absolute accuracy of clear-sky radiative transfer parameterizations; (c) identifying the robust impacts of aerosol radiative forcing during the historical period.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Characterizing forcings</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">ScenarioMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Scenario Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Facilitating integrated research on the impact of plausible future scenarios over physical and human systems, and on mitigation and adaptation options; (b) addressing targeted studies on the effects of particular forcings in collaboration with other MIPs; (c) help quantifying projection uncertainties based on multi-model ensembles and emergent constraints.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Scenarios</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">VolMIP</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Volcanic Forcings <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Model Intercom- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>parison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">(a) Assessing to what extent responses of the coupled ocean–atmosphere system to strong volcanic forcing are robustly simulated across state-of-the-art coupled climate models; (b) identifying the causes that limit robust simulated behaviour, especially differences in their treatment of physical processes</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Characterizing forcings</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">CORDEX<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Coordinated Re- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>gional Climate <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Downscaling Experiment</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Advancing and coordinating the science and application of regional climate downscaling (RCD) through statistical and dynamical downscaling of CMIP DECK, CMIP6 <italic>historical</italic>, and ScenarioMIP output.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Impacts</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">DynVarMIP<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Dynamics and Va- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>riability Model In- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>tercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Defining and analysing diagnostics that enable a mechanistic approach to confront model biases and understand the underlying causes behind circulation changes with a particular emphasis on the two-way coupling between the troposphere and the stratosphere.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Clouds/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Circulation</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">SIMIP<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Sea Ice Model <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Intercomparison Project</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Understanding the role of sea ice and its response to climate change by defining and analysing a comprehensive set of variables and process-oriented diagnostics that describe the sea ice state and its atmospheric and ocean forcing.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Ocean/Land/ <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Ice</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">VIACS AB<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Vulnerability, Im- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>pacts, Adaptation <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>and Climate <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>Services Advisory Board</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Facilitating a two-way dialogue between the CMIP6 modelling community and VIACS experts, who apply CMIP6 results for their numerous research and climate services, towards an informed construction of model scenarios and simulations and the design of online diagnostics, metrics, and visualization of relevance to society.</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Impacts</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:tbody>
   </oasis:tgroup></oasis:table></table-wrap>

      <p>Each of the 21 CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs is described in a separate invited
contribution to this special issue. These contributions will detail the goal
of the MIP and the major scientific gaps the MIP is addressing, and will
specify what is new compared to CMIP5 and previous CMIP phases. The
contributions will include a description of the experimental design and
scientific justification of each of the experiments for Tier 1 (and possibly
beyond), and will link the experiments and analysis to the DECK and CMIP6
historical simulations. They will additionally include an analysis plan to
fully justify the resources used to produce the various requested variables,
and if the analysis plan is to compare model results to observations, the
contribution will highlight possible model diagnostics and performance
metrics specifying whether the comparison entails any particular requirement
for the simulations or outputs (e.g. the use of observational simulators).
In addition, possible observations and reanalysis products for model
evaluation are discussed and the MIPs are encouraged to help facilitate
their use by contributing them to the obs4MIPs/ana4MIPs archives at the ESGF
(see Sect. 3.3). In some MIPs, additional forcings beyond those used in the
DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations are required, and these are described
in the respective contribution as well.
<?xmltex \hack{\newpage}?>
A number of MIPs are developments and/or continuation of long-standing
science themes. These include MIPs specifically addressing science questions
related to cloud feedback and the understanding of spatial patterns of
circulation and precipitation (CFMIP), carbon cycle feedback, and the
understanding of changes in carbon fluxes and stores (C<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>MIP), detection
and attribution (DAMIP) that newly includes 21st-century GHG-only
simulations allowing the projected responses to GHGs and other forcings to
be separated and scaled to derive observationally constrained projections,
and paleoclimate (PMIP), which assesses the credibility of the model
response to forcing outside the range of recent variability. These MIPs
reflect the importance of key forcing and feedback processes in
understanding past, present, and future climate change and have developed new
experiments and science plans focused on emerging new directions that will
be at the centre of the WCRP Grand Science Challenges. A few new MIPs have
arisen directly from gaps in understanding in CMIP5 (Stouffer
et al., 2015), for example, poor quantification of radiative forcing (RFMIP),
better understanding of ocean heat uptake and sea level rise (FAFMIP), and
understanding of model response to volcanic forcing (VolMIP).</p>
      <p>Since CMIP5, other MIPs have emerged as the modelling community has
developed more complex ESMs with interactive components beyond the carbon
cycle. These include the consistent quantification of forcings and feedback
from aerosols and atmospheric chemistry (AerChemMIP), and, for the first
time in CMIP, modelling of sea level rise from land ice sheets (ISMIP6).</p>
      <p>Some MIPs specifically target systematic biases focusing on improved
understanding of the sea ice state and its atmospheric and oceanic forcing
(SIMIP), the physical and biogeochemical aspects of the ocean (OMIP), land,
snow and soil moisture processes (LS3MIP), and improved understanding of
circulation and variability with a focus on stratosphere–troposphere
coupling (DynVarMIP). With the increased emphasis in the climate science
community on the need to represent and understand changes in regional
circulation, systematic biases are also addressed on a more regional scale
by the Global Monsoon MIP (GMMIP) and a first coordinated activity on high-resolution modelling (HighResMIP).</p>
      <p>For the first time, future scenario experiments, previously coordinated
centrally as part of the CMIP5 core experiments, will be run as an MIP
ensuring clear definition and well-coordinated science questions.
ScenarioMIP will run a new set of future long-term (century timescale)
integrations engaging input from both the climate science and integrated
assessment modelling communities. The new scenarios are based on a matrix
that uses the shared socioeconomic pathways (SSPs, O'Neill
et al., 2015) and forcing levels of the Representative Concentration
Pathways (RCP) as axes. As a set, they span the same range as the CMIP5 RCPs
(Moss et al., 2010), but fill critical gaps for intermediate forcing
levels and questions, for example, on short-lived species and land use. The
near-term experiments (10–30 years) are coordinated by the decadal climate
prediction project (DCPP) with improvements expected, for example, from the
initialization of additional components beyond the ocean and from a more
detailed process understanding and evaluation of the predictions to better
identify sources and limits of predictability.</p>
      <p>Other MIPs include specific future mitigation options, e.g. the land use MIP
(LUMIP) that is for the first time in CMIP isolating regional land
management strategies to study how different surface types respond to
climate change and direct anthropogenic modifications, or the geoengineering
MIP (GeoMIP), which examines climate impacts of newly proposed radiation
modification geoengineering strategies.</p>
      <p>The diagnostic MIP CORDEX will oversee the downscaling of CMIP6 models for
regional climate projections. Another historic development in our field that
provides, for the first time in CMIP, an avenue for a more formal
communication between the climate modelling and user community is the
endorsement of the vulnerability, impacts, and adaptation and climate
services advisory board (VIACS AB). This diagnostic MIP requests certain key
variables of interest to the VIACS community be delivered in a timely manner
to be used by climate services and in impact studies.</p>
      <p>All MIPs define output streams in the centrally coordinated CMIP6 data
request for each of their own experiments as well as the DECK and CMIP6
historical simulations (see the CMIP6 data request contribution to this
special issue for details). This will ensure that the required variables are
stored at the frequency and resolution required to address the specific
science questions and evaluation needs of each MIP and to enable a broad
characterization of the performance of the CMIP6 models.</p>
      <p>We note that only the Tier 1 MIP experiments are overseen by the CMIP Panel,
but additional experiments are proposed by the MIPs in Tiers 2 and 3. We
encourage the modelling groups to participate in the full suite of
experiments beyond Tier 1 to address in more depth the scientific questions
posed.</p>
      <p>The call for MIP applications for CMIP6 is still open and new proposals will
be reviewed at the annual WGCM meetings. However, we point out that the
additional MIPs suggested after the CMIP6 data request has been finalized
will have to work with the already defined model output from the DECK and
CMIP6 historical simulations, or work with the modelling group to recover
additional variables from their internal archives. We also point out that
some experiments proposed by CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs may not be finished until
after CMIP6 ends.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="Ch1.S5" sec-type="conclusions">
  <title>Summary</title>
      <p>CMIP6 continues the pattern of evolution and adaptation characteristic of
previous phases of CMIP. To centre CMIP at the heart of activities within
climate science and encourage links among activities within the World
Climate Research Programme (WCRP), CMIP6 has been formulated scientifically
around three specific questions, amidst the backdrop of the WCRP's seven
Grand Science Challenges. To meet the increasingly broad scientific demands
of the climate-science community, yet be responsive to the individual
priorities and resource limitations of the modelling centres, CMIP has
adopted a new, more federated organizational structure.</p>

      <?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><fig id="Ch1.F4" specific-use="star"><caption><p>CMIP6 timeline for the preparation of forcings, the realization of
experiments and their analysis.</p></caption>
        <?xmltex \igopts{width=369.885827pt}?><graphic xlink:href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/9/1937/2016/gmd-9-1937-2016-f04.png"/>

      </fig>

      <p>CMIP has now evolved from a centralized activity involving a large number of
experiments to a federated activity, encompassing many individually designed
MIPs. CMIP6 comprises 21 individual CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs and the DECK and
CMIP6 historical simulations. Four of the 21 CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs are
diagnostic in nature, meaning that they require additional output from
models, but not additional simulations. The total amount of output from
CMIP6 is estimated to be between 20 and 40 petabytes, depending on model
resolution and the number of modelling centres ultimately participating in
CMIP6. Questions addressed in the MIPs are wide ranging, from the climate of
distant past to the response of turbulent cloud processes to radiative
forcing, from how the terrestrial biosphere influences the uptake of
CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> to how much predictability is stored in the ocean, from how to best
project near-term to long-term future climate changes while considering
interdependence and differences in model performance in the CMIP6 ensemble,
and from what regulates the distribution of tropospheric ozone, to the
influence of land-use changes on water availability.</p>
      <p>The last 3 years have been dedicated to conceiving and then planning what
we now call CMIP6. Starting in 2016, the first modelling centres are
expected to begin performing the DECK and uploading output on the ESGF. Forcings
for the DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations will be ready before mid-2016 so that
these experiements can be started, and by the end of 2016 the diverse
forcings for different scenarios of future human activity will become available.
Past experience suggests that most centres will complete their CMIP simulations within a few years
while the analysis of CMIP6 results will likely go on for a decade or more
(Fig. 4).</p>
      <p>Through an intensified effort to align CMIP with specific scientific
questions and the WCRP Grand Science Challenges, we expect CMIP6 to continue
CMIP's tradition of major scientific advances. CMIP6 simulations and
scientific achievements are expected to support the IPCC Sixth Assessment
Report (AR6) as well as other national and international climate assessments
or special reports. Ultimately scientific progress on the most pressing
problems of climate variability and change will be the best measure of the
success of CMIP6.
<?xmltex \hack{\newpage}?></p>
<sec id="Ch1.S5.SSx1" specific-use="unnumbered">
  <title>Data availability</title>
      <p>The model output from the DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations described in
this paper  will be distributed through the Earth System Grid Federation
(ESGF) with digital object identifiers (DOIs) assigned. As in CMIP5, the
model output will be freely accessible through data portals after
registration. In order to document CMIP6's scientific impact and enable
ongoing support of CMIP, users are obligated to acknowledge CMIP6, the
participating modelling groups, and the ESGF centres (see details on the CMIP
Panel website at
<uri>http://www.wcrp-climate.org/index.php/wgcm-cmip/about-cmip</uri>). Further
information about the infrastructure supporting CMIP6, the metadata
describing the model output, and the terms governing its use are provided by
the WGCM Infrastructure Panel (WIP) in their invited contribution to this
special issue. Along with the data, the provenance of the data will be
recorded, and DOIs will be assigned to collections of output so that they can
be appropriately cited. This information will be made readily available so
that published research results can be verified and credit can be given to
the modelling groups providing the data. The WIP is coordinating and
encouraging the development of the infrastructure needed to archive and
deliver this information. In order to run the experiments, data sets for
natural and anthropogenic forcings are required. These forcing data sets are
described in separate invited contributions to this special issue. The
forcing data sets will be made available through the ESGF with version
control and DOIs assigned.</p><?xmltex \hack{\clearpage}?>
</sec>
</sec>

      
      </body>
    <back><app-group>

<app id="App1.Ch1.S1">
  <title>Experiment specifications</title>
<sec id="App1.Ch1.S1.SS1">
  <title>Specifications for the DECK</title>
      <p>Here we provide information needed to perform the DECK, including
specification of forcing and boundary conditions, initialization procedures,
and minimum length of runs. This information is largely consistent with but
not identical to the specifications for these experiments in CMIP5
(Taylor et al., 2009).</p>
      <p>The DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations are requested from all models
participating in CMIP. The expectation is that this requirement will be met
for each model configuration used in the subsequent CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs (an
entry card). For CMIP6, in the special case where the burden of the entry
card simulations is prohibitive but the scientific case for including a
particular model simulation is compelling (despite only partial completion
of the entry card simulations), an exception to this policy can be granted
on a model-by-model basis by the CMIP Panel, which will seek advice from the
chairs of the affected CMIP6-Endorsed MIP.</p>
      <p>CMIP6 is a cooperative effort across the international climate modelling and
climate science communities. The modelling groups have all been involved in
the design and implementation of CMIP6, and thus have agreed to a set of
best practices proposed for CMIP6. Those best practices include having the
modelling groups submit the DECK experiments and the CMIP6 historical
simulations to the ESGF, as well as any CMIP6-Endorsed MIP experiments they
choose to run. Additionally, the modelling groups decide what constitutes a
new model version. The CMIP Panel will work with the MIP co-chairs and the
modelling groups to ensure that these best practices are followed.</p>
<sec id="App1.Ch1.S1.SS1.SSS1">
  <title>AMIP simulation</title>
      <p>As in the first simulations performed under the Atmospheric Model
Intercomparison Project (AMIP, Gates et al., 1999), SSTs and SICs in AMIP experiments are prescribed consistent with
observations (see details on this forcing data set in the corresponding
contribution to this special issue). Land models should be configured as
close as possible to the one used in the CMIP6 historical simulation including
transient land use and land cover. Other external forcings including
volcanic aerosols, solar variability, GHG concentrations, and anthropogenic
aerosols should also be prescribed consistent with those used in the CMIP6
historical simulation (see Sect. A2 below). Even though in AMIP
simulations models with an active carbon cycle will not be fully
interactive, surface carbon fluxes should be archived over land.</p>
      <p>AMIP integrations can be initialized from prior model integrations or from
observations or in other reasonable ways. Depending on the treatment of snow
cover, soil water content, the carbon cycle, and vegetation, these runs may
require a spin-up period of several years. One might establish
quasi-equilibrium conditions consistent with the model by, for example,
running with ocean conditions starting earlier in the 1970s or cycling
repeatedly through year 1979 before simulating the official period. Results
from the spin-up period (i.e. prior to 1979) should be discarded, but the
spin-up technique should be documented.</p>
      <p>For CMIP6, AMIP simulations should cover at least the period from January 1979
through December 2014, but modelling groups are encouraged to extend
their runs to the end of the observed period. Output may also be contributed
from years preceding 1979 with the understanding that surface ocean
conditions were less complete and in some cases less reliable then.</p>
      <p>The climate found in AMIP simulations is largely determined by the
externally imposed forcing, especially the ocean conditions. Nevertheless,
unforced variability (noise) within the atmosphere introduces some
non-deterministic variations that hamper unambiguous interpretation of
apparent relationships between, for example, the year-to-year anomalies in
SSTs and their consequences over land. To assess the role of unforced
atmospheric variability in any particular result, modelling groups are
encouraged to generate an ensemble of AMIP simulations. For most studies, a
three-member ensemble, where only the initial conditions are varied, would
be the minimum required, with larger size ensembles clearly of value in
making more precise determination of statistical significance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="App1.Ch1.S1.SS1.SSS2">
  <title>Multi-century pre-industrial control simulations</title>
      <p>Like laboratory experiments, numerical experiments are designed to reveal
cause and effect relationships. A standard way of doing this is to perform
both a control experiment and a second experiment where some
externally imposed experiment condition has been altered. For many CMIP
experiments, including the rest of the experiments discussed in this
Appendix, the control is a simulation with atmospheric composition and
other conditions prescribed and held constant, consistent with best
estimates of the forcing from the historical period.</p>
      <p>Ideally the pre-industrial control (<italic>piControl</italic>) experiment for CMIP would represent a
near-equilibrium state of the climate system under the imposed conditions.
In reality, simulations of hundreds to many thousands of years would be
required for the ocean's depths to equilibrate and for biogeochemical
reservoirs to fully adjust. Available computational resources generally
preclude integrations long enough to approach equilibrium, so in practice
shorter runs must suffice. Usually, a <italic>piControl</italic> simulation is initialized from the
control run of a different model or from observations, and then run until at
least the surface climate conditions stabilize using 1850 forcings (see
Stouffer et al., 2004, for further discussion). This spin-up
period can be as long as several hundred years and variables that can
document the spin-up behaviour should be archived (under the experiment
labels <italic>piControl-spinup</italic> or <italic>esm-piControl-spinup</italic>). At the very least the length of the spin-up period should be
documented.</p>
      <p>Although equilibrium is generally not achieved, the changes occurring after
the spin-up period are usually found to evolve at a fairly constant rate
that presumably decreases slowly as equilibrium is approached. After a few
centuries, these drifts of the system mainly affect the carbon cycle and
ocean below the main thermocline, but they are also manifest at the surface
in a slow change in sea level. The climate drift must be removed in order to
interpret experiments that use the pre-industrial simulation as a control.
The usual procedure is to assume that the drift is insensitive to CMIP
experiment conditions and to simply subtract the control run from the
perturbed run to determine the climate change that would occur in the
absence of drift.</p>
      <p>Besides serving as controls for numerical experimentation, the
<italic>piControl</italic> and <italic>esm-piControl</italic> are used to study the naturally occurring, unforced variability of the
climate system. The only source of climate variability in a control arises
from processes internal to the model, whereas in the more complicated real
world, variations are also caused by external forcing factors such as solar
variability and changes in atmospheric composition caused, for example, by
human activities or volcanic eruptions. Consequently, the physical processes
responsible for unforced variability can more easily be isolated and studied
using the control run of models, rather than by analysing observations.</p>
      <p>A DECK control simulation is required to be long enough to extend to the end
of any perturbation runs initiated from it so that climate drift can be
assessed and possibly removed from those runs. If, for example, a historical
simulation (beginning in 1850) were initiated from the beginning of the
control simulation and then were followed by a future scenario run extending
to year 2300, a control run of at least 450 years would be required. As
discussed above, control runs are also used to assess model-simulated
unforced climate variability. The longer the control, the more precisely can
variability be quantified for any given timescale. A control simulation of
many hundreds of years would be needed to assess variability on centennial
timescales. For CMIP6 it is recommended that the control run should be at
least 500 years long (following the spin-up period), but of course the
simulation must be long enough to reach to the end of the experiments it
spawns. It should be noted that those analysing CMIP6 simulations might also
require simulations longer than 500 years to accurately assess unforced
variability on long timescales, so modelling groups are encouraged to
extend their control runs well beyond the minimum recommended number of
years.</p>
      <p>Because the climate was very likely not in equilibrium with the forcing of
1850 and because different components of the climate system differentially
respond to the effects of the forcing prior to that time, there is some
ambiguity in deciding on what forcing to apply for the control. For CMIP6 we
recommend a specification of this forcing that attempts to balance
conflicting objectives to
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item>
      <p>minimize artificial climate responses to discontinuities in radiative
forcing at the time a historical simulation is initiated, and</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>minimize artefacts in sea level change due to thermal expansion caused by
unrealistic mismatches in conditions in the centennial-scale averaged
forcings for the pre- and post-1850 periods. Note that any preindustrial
multi-centennial observed trend in global-mean sea level is most likely to
be due to slow changes in ice-sheets, which are likely not to be simulated
in the CMIP6 model generation.</p></list-item></list>
The first consideration above implies that radiative forcing in the control
run should be close to that imposed at the beginning of the CMIP historical
simulation (i.e. 1850). The second implies that a background volcanic
aerosol and time-averaged solar forcing should be prescribed in the control
run, since to neglect it would cause an apparent drift in sea level
associated with the suppression of heat uptake due to the net effect of, for
instance, volcanism after 1850, and this has implications for sea level
changes (Gregory, 2010; Gregory et al., 2013). We recognize that it will
be impossible to entirely avoid artefacts and artificial transient effects,
and practical considerations may rule out conformance with every detail of
the control simulation protocol stipulated here. With that understanding,
here is a summary of the recommendations for the imposed conditions on the
spin-up and control runs, followed by further clarification in subsequent
paragraphs:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item>
      <p>Conditions must be time invariant except for those associated with the mean
climate (notably the seasonal and diurnal cycles of insolation).</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>Unless indicated otherwise (e.g. the background volcanic forcing),
experiment conditions (e.g. greenhouse gas concentrations, ozone
concentration, surface land conditions) should be representative of Earth
around the year 1850.</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>Orbital parameters (eccentricity, obliquity, and longitude of the
perihelion) should be held fixed at their 1850 values.</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>Land use should not change in the control run and should be fixed according
to reconstructed agricultural maps from 1850. Due to the diversity of model
approaches in ESMs for land carbon, some groups might deviate from this
specification, and again this must be clearly documented.</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>The solar constant should be fixed at its mean value (no 11-year solar
cycle) over the first two solar cycles of the historical simulation (i.e.
the 1850–1873 mean).</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>A background volcanic aerosol should be specified that results in radiative
forcing matching, as closely as possible, that experienced, on average,
during the historical simulation (i.e. 1850–2014 mean).</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>Models without interactive ozone chemistry should specify the pre-industrial
ozone fields from a data set produced from a pre-industrial control
simulation that uses 1850 emissions and a mean solar forcing averaged over
solar cycles 8–10, representative of the mean mid-19th century solar
forcing.</p></list-item><list-item>
      <p>For models with interactive chemistry and/or aerosols, the CMIP6 pre-industrial
emissions dataset of reactive gases and aerosol precursors should be used. For models
without internally calculated aerosol concentrations, a monthly climatological dataset
of aerosol physical and optical properties should be used.</p></list-item></list>
In the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-concentration-driven <italic>piControl</italic>, the value of the global annual mean 1850 atmospheric CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration is prescribed and held fixed during the entire experiment. There are some special considerations that apply to control simulations
performed by emission-driven ESMs (i.e. runs with atmospheric
concentrations of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> calculated prognostically rather than being
prescribed). In the <italic>esm-piControl</italic> simulation, emissions of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> from both fossil fuel
combustion and land-use change are prescribed to be zero. In this run any
residual drift in atmospheric CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration that arises from an
imbalance in the exchanges of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> between the atmosphere and the ocean
and land (i.e. by the natural carbon cycle in the absence of anthropogenic
CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> emissions) will need to be subtracted from perturbation runs to
correct for a control state not in equilibrium. It should be emphasized that
the <italic>esm-piControl</italic> is an idealized experiment and is not meant to mimic the true 1850
conditions, which would have to include a source of carbon of around 0.6 Pg C yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> from the already perturbed state that existed in 1850.</p>
      <p>Due to a wide variety of ESMs and the techniques they use to compute land
carbon fluxes, it is hard to make statements that apply to all models
equally well. A general recommendation, however, is that the land carbon
fluxes in the emission and concentration-driven control simulations should
be stable in time and in approximate balance so that the net carbon flux
into the atmosphere is small (less than 0.1 Pg C yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>). Further details on ESM
experiments with a carbon cycle are provided in the C<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>MIP contribution
to this special issue.</p>
      <p>The historical time-average volcanic forcing stipulated above for the
control run is likely to approximate the much longer term mean.
The volcanic aerosol radiative forcing estimates of Crowley (2000) for the historical
period and the last millennium are <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>0.18 and <inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>0.22 W m<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>,
respectively. Because the mean volcanic forcing between 1850 and 2014 is
small, the discontinuity associated with transitioning from a mean forcing
to a time-varying volcanic forcing is also expected to be small. Even though
this is the design objective, it is likely that it will be impossible to
eliminate all artefacts in quantities such as historical sea level change.
For this reason, and because some models may deviate from these
specifications, it is recommended that groups perform an additional
simulation of the historical period but with only natural forcing included.
With this additional run, which is already called for under DAMIP, the
purely anthropogenic effects on sea level change can be isolated.</p>
      <p>The forcing specified in the <italic>piControl</italic> also has implications for simulations of the
future, when solar variability and volcanic activity will continue to exist,
but at unknown levels. These issues need to be borne in mind when designing
and evaluating future scenarios, as a failure to include volcanic forcing in
the future will cause future warming and sea level rise to be over-estimated
relative to a <italic>piControl</italic> experiment in which a non-zero volcanic forcing is specified.
This is accounted for by introducing a time-invariant non-zero volcanic
forcing (e.g. the mean volcanic forcing for the <italic>piControl</italic>) into the scenarios. This
is further specified in the ScenarioMIP contribution to this special issue.</p>
      <p>These issues, and the potential of different modelling centres adopting
different approaches to account for their particular constraints, highlight
the paramount importance of adequately documenting the conditions under
which this and the other DECK experiments are performed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="App1.Ch1.S1.SS1.SSS3">
  <?xmltex \opttitle{Abruptly quadrupling CO${}_{{2}}$ simulation}?><title>Abruptly quadrupling CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> simulation</title>
      <p>Until CMIP5, there were no experiments designed to quantify the extent to
which forcing differences might explain differences in climate response. It
was also difficult to diagnose and quantify the feedback responses, which
are mediated by global surface temperature change (Sherwood et al.,
2015). In order to examine these fundamental characteristics of models –
CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> forcing and climate feedback – an abrupt 4<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> simulation was
included for the first time as part of CMIP5. Following
Gregory et al. (2004), the simulation branches in
January of the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-concentration-driven <italic>piControl</italic> and
abruptly the value of the global annual mean 1850 atmospheric CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration
that is prescribed in <italic>piControl</italic> is quadrupled and held fixed. As the system
subsequently evolves toward a new equilibrium, the imbalance in the net flux
at the top of the atmosphere can be plotted against global temperature
change. As Gregory et al. (2004) showed, it is then
possible to diagnose both the effective radiative forcing due to a
quadrupling of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and also effective equilibrium climate sensitivity
(ECS). Moreover, by examining how individual flux components evolve with
surface temperature change, one can learn about the relative strengths of
different feedback, notably quantifying the importance of various feedback
associated with clouds.</p>
      <p>In the <italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> experiment, the only externally imposed difference from the
<italic>piControl</italic> should be the change in CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration. All other conditions should
remain as they were in the <italic>piControl</italic>, including any background volcanic aerosols. By
changing only a single factor, we can unambiguously attribute all climatic
consequences to the increase in CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration.</p>
      <p>The minimum length of the  simulation should be 150 years, but longer
simulations would enable investigations of longer-timescale responses. Also
there is value, as in CMIP5, in performing an ensemble of short
(<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> 5-year) simulations, all prescribing global annual mean 1850
atmospheric CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration but initiated at different times throughout
the year (in addition to the <italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> simulation initiated from the <italic>piControl</italic> in January). Such an ensemble would
reduce the statistical uncertainty with which the effective CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
radiative forcing could be quantified and would allow more detailed and
accurate diagnosis of the fast responses of the system under an abrupt
change in forcing (Bony et al., 2013; Gregory and Webb, 2008; Kamae and
Watanabe, 2013; Sherwood et al., 2015). Different groups will be able to
afford ensembles of different sizes, but in any case each realization should
be initialized in a different month and the months should be spaced evenly
throughout the year.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="App1.Ch1.S1.SS1.SSS4">
  <?xmltex \opttitle{1\,{\%} CO${}_{{2}}$ increase simulation}?><title>1 % CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> increase simulation</title>
      <p>The second idealized climate change experiment was introduced in the early
days of CMIP (Meehl et al., 2000). It is designed for
studying model responses under simplified but somewhat more realistic
forcing than an abrupt increase in CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. In this <italic>1pctCO2</italic> experiment, the
simulation is branched from the <italic>piControl</italic>, and the global annual mean CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration is gradually
increased at a rate of 1 % yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> (i.e. exponentially), starting from its 1850 value that is prescribed in the <italic>piControl</italic>. A minimum
length of 150 years is requested so that the simulation goes beyond the
quadrupling of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> after 140 years. Note that in contrast to previous
definitions, the experiment has been simplified so that the 1 % CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
increase per year is applied throughout the entire simulation rather than
keeping it constant after 140 years as in CMIP5. Since the radiative forcing
is approximately proportional to the logarithm of the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> increase, the
radiative forcing linearly increases over time. Drawing on the estimates of
effective radiative forcing (for definitions see Myhre et al., 2013) obtained in the
<italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> simulations, analysts can scale results from each model in the 1 %
CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> increase simulations to focus on the response differences in
models, largely independent of their forcing differences. In contrast, in
CMIP6 historical simulations (see Sect. A2), the forcing and response
contributions to model differences in simulated climate change cannot be
easily isolated.</p>
      <p>As in the <italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic> experiment, the only externally imposed difference from the
<italic>piControl</italic> should be the change in CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration. The omission of changes in
aerosol concentrations is the key to making these simulations easier to
interpret.</p>
      <p>Models with a carbon cycle component will be driven by prescribed CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
concentrations, but terrestrial and marine surface fluxes and stores of
carbon will become a key diagnostic from which one can infer emission rates
that are consistent with a 1 % yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> increase in model CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
concentration. This DECK baseline carbon cycle experiment is built upon in
C<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>MIP to diagnose the strength of model carbon climate feedback and to
quantify contributions to disruption of the carbon cycle by climate and by
direct effects of increased CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="App1.Ch1.S1.SS2">
  <title>The CMIP6 historical simulations</title>
      <p>CMIP6 historical simulations of climate change over the period 1850–2014
are forced by common data sets that are largely based on observations.
They serve as an important benchmark for assessing model performance through
evaluation against observations. The historical integration should be
initialized from some point in the control integration (with <italic>historical</italic> branching from
the <italic>piControl</italic> and the <italic>esm-hist</italic> branching from <italic>esm-piControl</italic>) and be forced by varying time,
externally imposed conditions that are based on observations. Both
naturally forced changes (e.g. due to solar variability and volcanic
aerosols) and changes due to human activities (e.g. CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration,
aerosols, and land use) will lead to climate variations and evolution. In
addition, there is unforced variability which can obscure the forced changes
and lead to expected differences between the simulated and observed climate
variations (Deser et al., 2012).</p>
      <p>The externally imposed forcing data sets that should be used in CMIP6 cover
the period 1850 through the end of 2014 and are described in detail in various
other contributions to this special issue. In the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-concentration-driven historical simulations, time-varying global
annual mean concentrations for CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and other long-lived greenhouse gases are
prescribed. If a modelling center decides to represent additional spatial and
seasonal variations in prescribed greenhouse gas forcings, this needs to be
adequately documented.</p>
      <p>Recall from Sect. A1.2 that the
conditions in the control should generally be consistent with the forcing
imposed near the beginning of the CMIP historical simulation. This should
minimize artificial transient effects in the first portion of the CMIP
historical simulation. An exception is that for the CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>-emission-driven
experiments, the zero CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> emissions from fossil fuel and the land-use
specifications for 1850 in the <italic>esm-piControl</italic> could cause a discontinuity in land carbon
at the branch point.</p>

<?xmltex \floatpos{t}?><table-wrap id="App1.Ch1.T1" specific-use="star"><caption><p>Specifications in the DECK and CMIP6 historical simulations.</p></caption><oasis:table frame="topbot"><?xmltex \begin{scaleboxenv}{.98}[.98]?><oasis:tgroup cols="4">
     <oasis:colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="left"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="justify" colwidth="142.26378pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="justify" colwidth="113.811024pt"/>
     <oasis:colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="justify" colwidth="147.954331pt"/>
     <oasis:thead>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1">Experiment</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Volcanic stratospheric aerosol</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Solar variability</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Anthropogenic forcings</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:thead>
     <oasis:tbody>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>amip</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Time-dependent observations</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Time-dependent observations</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Time-dependent observations</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Background volcanic aerosol that <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>results in radiative forcing matching, as <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>closely as possible, that was experienced, on average, during the historical simulation (i.e. 1850–2014 mean)</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Fixed at its mean value (no <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>11-year solar cycle) over the <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>first two solar cycles of the <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>historical simulation (i.e. the <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>1850–1873 mean)</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Given that the historical simulations <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>start in 1850, the <italic>piControl</italic> should have <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>fixed 1850 atmospheric composition, <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>not true pre-industrial</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>esm-piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">As in <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">As in <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">As in <italic>piControl</italic> but with CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concen- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>tration calculated, rather than prescribed. <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> from both fossil fuel combustion <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>and land-use change are prescribed to be <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>zero.</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>abrupt-4</italic><inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>CO2</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">As in <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">As in <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">As in <italic>piControl </italic>except CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> that is 4 <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>times that of <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>1pctCO2</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">As in <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">As in <italic>piControl</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">As in <italic>piControl </italic>except CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> that is <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>increasing at 1 % yr<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row rowsep="1">  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>historical</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">Time-dependent observations</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">Time-dependent observations</oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">Time-dependent observations</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
       <oasis:row>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col1"><italic>esm-hist</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col2">As in <italic>historical</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col3">As in <italic>historical</italic></oasis:entry>  
         <oasis:entry colname="col4">As in <italic>historical</italic> but with CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> emissions <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>prescribed and CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> concentration calcu- <?xmltex \hack{\hfill\break}?>lated (rather than prescribed)</oasis:entry>
       </oasis:row>
     </oasis:tbody>
   </oasis:tgroup><?xmltex \end{scaleboxenv}?></oasis:table></table-wrap>

      <p>As described in Sect. A1.2, the 1850 <italic>esm-piControl</italic> should be developed for an idealized
case that is stable in time and balance so that the net carbon flux into the
atmosphere is small. Meanwhile, the start of the <italic>esm-hist</italic> in 1850 should be as
realistic as possible and attempt to account for the fact the land surface
was not in equilibrium in 1850 due to prior land-use effects (Houghton,
2010; Hurtt et al., 2011). Some modelling groups have developed methods to
achieve these twin goals in a computationally efficient manner, for example,
by performing pre-1850 off-line land model simulations to account for the
land carbon cycle disequilibrium before 1850 and to adequately simulate
carbon stores at the start of the historical simulation (Sentman
et al., 2011). Due to the wide diversity of modelling approaches for land
carbon in the ESMs, the actual method applied by each group to account for
these effects will differ and needs to be well documented.</p>
      <p>As discussed earlier, there will be a mismatch in the specification of
volcanic aerosols between control and historical simulations that especially
affect estimates of ocean heat uptake and sea level rise in the historical
period. This can be minimized by prescribing a background volcanic aerosol
in the pre-industrial control that has the same cooling effect as the
volcanoes included in the CMIP6 historical simulation. Any residual mismatch
will need to be corrected, which requires a special supplementary simulation
(see Sect. A1.2) that should be submitted along with the CMIP6 historical
simulation.</p>
      <p>For model evaluation and for detection and attribution studies (the focus of
DAMIP) there would be considerable value in extending the CMIP6 historical
simulations beyond the nominal 2014 ending date. To include the more recent
observations in model evaluation, modelling groups are encouraged to
document and apply forcing data sets representing the post-2014 period. For
short extensions (up to a few years) it may be acceptable to simply apply
forcing from one of the future scenarios defined by ScenarioMIP. To
distinguish between the portion of the historical period when all models
will use the same forcing data sets (i.e. 1850–2014) from the extended
period where different data sets might be used, the experiment for 1850–2014
will be labelled <italic>historical</italic> (<italic>esm-hist</italic> in the case of the emission-driven run)
and the period from 2015 through near-present will likely be labelled
<italic>historical-ext</italic> (<italic>esm-hist-ext</italic>).</p>
      <p>Even if the CMIP6 historical simulations are extended beyond 2014, all
future scenario simulations (called for by ScenarioMIP and other MIPs)
should be initiated from the end of year 2014 of the CMIP6 historical
simulation since the “future” in CMIP6 begins in 2015.</p>
      <p>Due to interactions within and between the components of the Earth system,
there is a wide range of variability on various time and space scales
(Hegerl et al., 2007). The timescales  vary
from shorter than a day to longer than several centuries. The magnitude of
the variability can be quite large relative to any given signal of interest
depending on the time and space scales involved and on the variable of
interest. To more clearly identify forced signals emerging from natural
variability, multiple model integrations (comprising an ensemble) can be
made where only the initial conditions are perturbed in some way which
should be documented. A common way to do this is to simply branch each
simulation from a different point in the control run. Longer intervals
between branch points will ensure independence of ensemble members on longer
timescales. By averaging many different ensemble members together, the
signal of interest becomes clear because the natural variations tend to
average out if the ensemble size and averaging period are long enough. If
the variability in the models is realistic, then the spread of the ensemble
members around the ensemble average is caused by unforced (i.e. internal)
variability. To minimize the number of years included in the entry card
simulations, only one ensemble member is requested here. However, we
strongly encourage model groups to submit at least three ensemble members of
their CMIP historical simulation as requested in DAMIP.</p><?xmltex \hack{\clearpage}?>
</sec>
</app>
  </app-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the scientific community for their engagement in the definition of
CMIP6 and for the broad participation in the CMIP5 survey in 2013. We thank
the co-chairs and steering committee members of the CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs for
their continuous engagement in defining CMIP6, and the modelling groups and
wider community for reviewing the CMIP6 design and organization. We thank the
WGCM Infrastructure Panel (WIP) for overseeing the CMIP6 infrastructure,
Martin Juckes for taking the lead in preparing the CMIP6 data request,
and the group of scientists who are producing forcing datasets for CMIP6. Thanks to Jonathan Gregory for raising awareness about the treatment of volcanic
forcing in the pre-industrial control experiment and its consequence for sea
level changes, and to Pierre Friedlingstein, George Hurtt, Chris Jones, and
David Lawrence for help in defining carbon cycle and land-use specifications
in the DECK experiments and CMIP6 historical simulations. Norbert Noreiks is
thanked for help in drafting the figures. Thanks to our topical editor Julia Hargreaves,
to Gavin Schmidt and the other two anonymous reviewers, and to
everyone who contributed to the open discussions for constructive comments.
GM and KET were supported by the Regional and Global Climate Modeling Program
(RGCM) of the U.S. Department of Energy's Office of Biological &amp;
Environmental Research (BER) (through Cooperative Agreement no.
DE-FC02-97ER62402 for GM), and GM received additional support from the U.S.
National Science Foundation. The National Center for Atmospheric Research is
sponsored by the National Science Foundation.<?xmltex \hack{\newline}?><?xmltex \hack{\newline}?>
The article processing charges
for this open-access <?xmltex \hack{\newline}?> publication were covered by a Research
<?xmltex \hack{\newline}?> Centre of the Helmholtz Association.<?xmltex \hack{\newline}?><?xmltex \hack{\newline}?>
Edited by: J. Hargreaves</p></ack><ref-list>
    <title>References</title>

      <ref id="bib1.bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation>
Bony, S., Bellon, G., Klocke, D., Sherwood, S., Fermepin, S., and Denvil,
S.: Robust direct effect of carbon dioxide on tropical circulation and
regional precipitation, Nat. Geosci., 6, 447–451, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation>
Bony, S., Stevens, B., Frierson, D. M. W., Jakob, C., Kageyama, M., Pincus,
R., Shepherd, T. G., Sherwood, S. C., Siebesma, A. P., Sobel, A. H.,
Watanabe, M., and Webb, M. J.: Clouds, circulation and climate sensitivity,
Nat. Geosci., 8, 261–268, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation>Brasseur, G. and Carlson, D.: Future directions for the World Climate
Research Programme, Eos, Transactions American Geophysical Union, 96,
<ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2015EO033577" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1029/2015EO033577</ext-link>,
2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation>CMIP Panel:  WCRP Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP), available
at: <uri>http://www.wcrp-climate.org/index.php/wgcm-cmip/about-cmip</uri>, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation>
Crowley, T. J.: Causes of climate change over the past 1000 years, Science, 289, 270–277, 2000.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation>
Cubasch, U., Wuebbles, D., Chen, D., Facchini, M. C., Frame, D., Mahowald, N., and
Winther, J.-G.: Introduction, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science
Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Stocker, T. F., Qin, D.,
Plattner, G.-K., Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia, Y.,
Bex, V., and Midgley, P. M., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and
New York, NY, USA, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation>
Deser, C., Knutti, R., Solomon, S., and Phillips, A. S.: Communication of the
role of natural variability in future North American climate, Nat. Clim.
Change, 2, 775–779, 2012.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation>Eyring, V., Righi, M., Lauer, A., Evaldsson, M., Wenzel, S., Jones, C., Anav, A., Andrews, O., Cionni, I., Davin,
E. L., Deser, C., Ehbrecht, C., Friedlingstein, P., Gleckler, P., Gottschaldt, K.-D., Hagemann, S.,
Juckes, M., Kindermann, S., Krasting, J., Kunert, D., Levine, R., Loew, A., Mäkelä, J., Martin, G.,
Mason, E., Phillips, A. S., Read, S., Rio, C., Roehrig, R., Senftleben, D., Sterl, A., van Ulft, L. H., Walton, J., Wang, S., and Williams,
K. D.: ESMValTool (v1.0) – a community diagnostic and performance metrics tool for routine evaluation of
Earth system models in CMIP, Geosci. Model Dev., 9, 1747–1802, <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/gmd-9-1747-2016" ext-link-type="DOI">10.5194/gmd-9-1747-2016</ext-link>, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation>Ferraro, R., Waliser, D. E., Gleckler, P., Taylor, K. E., and Eyring, V.:
Evolving obs4MIPs to Support the Sixth Coupled Model Intercomparison Project
(CMIP6), B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-14-00216.1" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1175/BAMS-D-14-00216.1</ext-link>, online
first,
2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation>
Flato, G., Marotzke, J., Abiodun, B., Braconnot, P., Chou, S. C., Collins,
W., Cox, P., Driouech, F., Emori, S., Eyring, V., Forest, C., Gleckler, P.,
Guilyardi, E., Jakob, C., Kattsov, V., Reason, C., and Rummukainen, M.:
Evaluation of Climate Models, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science
Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Stocker, T. F., Qin,
D., Plattner, G.-K., Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia,
Y., Bex, V., and Midgley, P. M., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK
and New York, NY, USA, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation>
Gates, W. L., Boyle, J. S., Covey, C., Dease, C. G., Doutriaux, C. M., Drach,
R. S., Fiorino, M., Gleckler, P. J., Hnilo, J. J., Marlais, S. M., Phillips,
T. J., Potter, G. L., Santer, B. D., Sperber, K. R., Taylor, K. E., and
Williams, D. N.: An Overview of the Results of the Atmospheric Model
Intercomparison Project (AMIP I), B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 80, 29–55, 1999.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation>
Geoffroy, O., Saint-Martin, D., Olivie, D. J. L., Voldoire, A., Bellon, G.,
and Tyteca, S.: Transient Climate Response in a Two-Layer Energy-Balance
Model. Part I: Analytical Solution and Parameter Calibration Using CMIP5
AOGCM Experiments, J. Climate, 26, 1841–1857, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation>Gleckler, P. J., Doutriaux, C., Durack P. J., Taylor K. E., Zhang, Y.,
Williams, D. N., Mason, E., and Servonnat, J.: A More Powerful Reality Test
for Climate Models, Eos Trans. AGU, <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2016EO051663" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1029/2016EO051663</ext-link>, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation>Gregory, J. and Webb, M.: Tropospheric adjustment induces a cloud component
in CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> forcing, J. Climate, 21, 58–71, 2008.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation>Gregory, J. M.: Long-term effect of volcanic forcing on ocean heat content,
Geophys. Res. Lett., 37, L22701, <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2010gl045507" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1029/2010gl045507</ext-link>, 2010.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation>Gregory, J. M., Ingram, W. J., Palmer, M. A., Jones, G. S., Stott, P. A.,
Thorpe, R. B., Lowe, J. A., Johns, T. C., and Williams, K. D.: A new method
for diagnosing radiative forcing and climate sensitivity, Geophys. Res.
Lett., 31, L03205, <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2003gl018747" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1029/2003gl018747</ext-link>, 2004.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation>
Gregory, J. M., Bi, D., Collier, M. A., Dix, M. R., Hirst, A. C., Hu, A.,
Huber, M., Knutti, R., Marsland, S. J., Meinshausen, M., Rashid, H. A.,
Rotstayn, L. D., Schurer, A., and Church, J. A.: Climate models without
preindustrial volcanic forcing underestimate historical ocean thermal
expansion, Geophys. Res. Lett., 40, 1600–1604, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation>
Hegerl, G. C., Zwiers, F. W., Braconnot, P., Gillett, N. P., Luo, Y., Marengo
Orsini, J. A., Nicholls, N., Penner, J. E., and Stott, P. A.: Understanding
and Attributing Climate Change, in: Climate Change 2007: The Physical Science
Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fourth Assessment Report of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Solomon, S., Qin, D.,
Manning, M., Chen, Z., Marquis, M., Averyt, K. B., Tignor, M., and Miller, H.
L., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York, NY, USA, 2007.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation>Houghton, R. A.: How well do we know the flux of CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> from land-use
change?, Tellus B, 62, 337–351, 2010.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation>
Hurtt, G. C., Chini, L. P., Frolking, S., Betts, R. A., Feddema, J., Fischer,
G., Fisk, J. P., Hibbard, K., Houghton, R. A., Janetos, A., Jones, C. D.,
Kindermann, G., Kinoshita, T., Goldewijk, K. K., Riahi, K., Shevliakova, E.,
Smith, S., Stehfest, E., Thomson, A., Thornton, P., van Vuuren, D. P., and
Wang, Y. P.: Harmonization of land-use scenarios for the period 1500–2100:
600 years of global gridded annual land-use transitions, wood harvest, and
resulting secondary lands, Climatic Change, 109, 117–161, 2011.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation>
IPCC: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of
Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel
on Climate Change, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York,
NY, USA, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation>Kamae, Y. and Watanabe, M.: Tropospheric adjustment to increasing CO<inline-formula><mml:math display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi/><mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>:
its timescale and the role of land-sea contrast, Clim. Dynam., 41,
3007–3024, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation>Lawrence, B. N., Balaji, V., Bentley, P., Callaghan, S., DeLuca, C., Denvil,
S., Devine, G., Elkington, M., Ford, R. W., Guilyardi, E., Lautenschlager,
M., Morgan, M., Moine, M.-P., Murphy, S., Pascoe, C., Ramthun, H., Slavin,
P., Steenman-Clark, L., Toussaint, F., Treshansky, A., and Valcke, S.:
Describing Earth system simulations with the Metafor CIM, Geosci. Model Dev.,
5, 1493–1500, <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/gmd-5-1493-2012" ext-link-type="DOI">10.5194/gmd-5-1493-2012</ext-link>, 2012.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation>
Li, C., Stevens, B., and Marotzke, J.: Eurasian winter cooling in the warming
hiatus of 1998–2012, Geophys. Res. Lett., 42, 8131–8139, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Boer, G. J., Covey, C., Latif, M., and Stouffer, R. J.:
Intercomparison makes for a better climate model, Eos, Transactions American
Geophysical Union, 78, 445–451, 1997.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Boer, G. J., Covey, C., Latif, M., and Stouffer, R. J.: The
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP), B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 81,
313–318, 2000.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Covey, C., Taylor, K. E., Delworth, T., Stouffer, R. J., Latif,
M., McAvaney, B., and Mitchell, J. F. B.: THE WCRP CMIP3 Multimodel Dataset:
A New Era in Climate Change Research, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 88, 1383–1394,
2007.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation>Meehl, G. A., Moss, R., Taylor, K. E., Eyring, V., Stouffer, R. J., Bony, S.,
and Stevens, B.: Climate Model Intercomparisons: Preparing for the Next
Phase, Eos Trans. AGU, 59, 77, <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2014EO090001" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1002/2014EO090001</ext-link>,  2014.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation>
Moss, R. H., Edmonds, J. A., Hibbard, K. A., Manning, M. R., Rose, S. K., van
Vuuren, D. P., Carter, T. R., Emori, S., Kainuma, M., Kram, T., Meehl, G. A.,
Mitchell, J. F. B., Nakicenovic, N., Riahi, K., Smith, S. J., Stouffer, R.
J., Thomson, A. M., Weyant, J. P., and Wilbanks, T. J.: The next generation
of scenarios for climate change research and assessment, Nature, 463,
747–756, 2010.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation>
Murphy, J. M. and Mitchell, J. F. B.: Transient-Response of the Hadley-Center
Coupled Ocean-Atmosphere Model to Increasing Carbon-Dioxide. 2. Spatial and
Temporal Structure of Response, J. Climate, 8, 57–80, 1995.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation>
Myhre, G., Shindell, D., Breìon, F.-M., Collins, W., Fuglestvedt, J.,
Huang, J., Koch, D., Lamarque, J.-F., Lee, D., Mendoza, B., Nakajima, T., Robock, A., Stephens,
G., Takemura, T., and Zhang, H.: Anthropogenic and Natural Radiative
Forcing, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of
Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel
on Climate Change, edited by: Stocker, T. F., Qin, D., Plattner, G.-K.,
Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia, Y., Bex, V., and
Midgley, P. M., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York, NY,
USA, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation>O'Neill, B. C., Kriegler, E., Ebi, K. L., Kemp-Benedict, E., Riahi, K.,
Rothman, D. S., van Ruijven, B. J., van Vuuren, D. P., Birkmann, J., Kok, K.,
Levy, M., and Solecki, W.: The roads ahead: Narratives for shared
socioeconomic pathways describing world futures in the 21st century, Global
Environ. Chang., <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.01.004" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.01.004</ext-link>, online first,
2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation>
Phillips, A. S., Deser, C., and Fasullo, J.: Evaluating Modes of Variability
in Climate Models, Eos Trans. AGU, 95, 453–455, 2014.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation>
Rauser, F., Gleckler, P., and Marotzke, J.: Rethinking the Default
Construction of Multimodel Climate Ensembles, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 96,
911–919, 2014.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation>
Sentman, L. T., Shevliakova, E., Stouffer, R. J., and Malyshev, S.: Time
Scales of Terrestrial Carbon Response Related to Land-Use Application:
Implications for Initializing an Earth System Model, Earth Interact., 15,
1–16, 2011.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation>
Sherwood, S. C., Bony, S., Boucher, O., Bretherton, C., Forster, P. M.,
Gregory, J. M., and Stevens, B.: Adjustments in the Forcing-Feedback
Framework for Understanding Climate Change, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 96,
217–228, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation>
Stevens, B.: Rethinking the Lower Bound on Aerosol Radiative Forcing, J.
Climate, 28, 4794–4819, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation>
Stott, P. A., Mitchell, J. F. B., Allen, M. R., Delworth, T. L., Gregory, J.
M., Meehl, G. A., and Santer, B. D.: Observational constraints on past
attributable warming and predictions of future global warming, J. Climate,
19, 3055–3069, 2006.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation>
Stouffer, R. J., Weaver, A. J., and Eby, M.: A method for obtaining
pre-twentieth century initial conditions for use in climate change studies,
Clim. Dynam., 23, 327–339, 2004.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation>
Stouffer, R. J., Eyring, V., Meehl, G. A., Bony, S., Senior, C., Stevens, B.,
and Taylor, K. E.: CMIP5 Scientific Gaps and Recommendations for CMIP6, B.
Am. Meteorol. Soc., submitted, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation>Taylor, K. E., Stouffer, R. J., and Meehl, G. A.: A Summary of the CMIP5
Experiment Design, available at:
<uri>http://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/docs/Taylor_CMIP5_design.pdf</uri> (last access:
13 May 2016), 2009.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation>
Taylor, K. E., Stouffer, R. J., and Meehl, G. A.: An Overview of Cmip5 and
the Experiment Design, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 93, 485–498, 2012.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation>Teixeira, J., Waliser, D., Ferraro, R., Gleckler, P., Lee, T., and Potter,
G.: Satellite Observations for CMIP5: The Genesis of Obs4MIPs, B. Am.
Meteorol. Soc., 95, 1329–1334, 2014.
 </mixed-citation></ref><?xmltex \hack{\newpage}?>
      <ref id="bib1.bib44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation>
Trenberth, K. and Asrar, G.: Challenges and Opportunities in Water Cycle
Research: WCRP Contributions, Surv. Geophys., 35, 515–532, 2014.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation>van Vuuren, D. P., Edmonds, J., Kainuma, M., Riahi, K., Thomson, A., Hibbard,
K., Hurtt, G. C., Kram, T., Krey, V., Lamarque, J. F., Masui, T.,
Meinshausen, M., Nakicenovic, N., Smith, S. J., and Rose, S. K.: The
representative concentration pathways: an overview, Climatic Change, 109,
5–31, 2011.
 </mixed-citation></ref><?xmltex \hack{\newpage}?>
      <ref id="bib1.bib46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation>Williams, D. N., Balaji, V., Cinquini, L., Denvil, S., Duffy, D., Evans, B.,
Ferraro, R., Hansen, R., Lautenschlager, M., and Trenham, C.: A Global
Repository for Planet-Sized Experiments and Observations, B. Am. Meteorol.
Soc., <ext-link xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/bams-d-15-00132.1" ext-link-type="DOI">10.1175/bams-d-15-00132.1</ext-link>, online first, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref>
      <ref id="bib1.bib47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation>
Williams, K. and Webb, M.: A quantitative performance assessment of cloud
regimes in climate models, Clim. Dynam., 33, 141–157, 2009.</mixed-citation></ref>

  </ref-list><app-group content-type="float"><app><title/>

    </app></app-group></back>
    <!--<article-title-html>Overview of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 6 (CMIP6)
experimental design and organization</article-title-html>
<abstract-html><p class="p">By coordinating the design and distribution of global
climate model simulations of the past, current,  and future climate, the
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) has become one of the
foundational elements of climate science. However, the need to address an
ever-expanding range of scientific questions arising from more and more
research communities has made it necessary to revise the organization of
CMIP. After a long and wide community consultation, a new and more federated
structure has been put in place. It consists of three major elements: (1) a
handful of common experiments, the DECK (Diagnostic, Evaluation and
Characterization of Klima) and CMIP historical simulations (1850–near present) that will maintain continuity and help document basic
characteristics of models across different phases of CMIP; (2) common
standards, coordination, infrastructure, and documentation that will
facilitate the distribution of model outputs and the characterization of the
model ensemble; and (3) an ensemble of CMIP-Endorsed Model Intercomparison
Projects (MIPs) that will be specific to a particular phase of CMIP (now
CMIP6) and that will build on the DECK and CMIP historical simulations to
address a large range of specific questions and fill the scientific gaps of
the previous CMIP phases. The DECK and CMIP historical simulations, together
with the use of CMIP data standards, will be the entry cards for models
participating in CMIP. Participation in CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs by individual
modelling groups will be at their own discretion and will depend on their
scientific interests and priorities. With the Grand Science Challenges of
the World Climate Research Programme (WCRP) as its scientific backdrop,
CMIP6 will address three broad questions:
<ul class="itemize"><li class="item"><div class="para"><p class="p">How does the Earth system
respond to forcing?</p></div></li><li class="item"><div class="para"><p class="p">What are the origins and consequences of
systematic model biases?</p></div></li><li class="item"><div class="para"><p class="p">How can we assess future climate changes
given internal climate variability, predictability, and uncertainties in
scenarios?</p></div></li></ul>
This CMIP6 overview paper presents the background and rationale
for the new structure of CMIP, provides a detailed description of the DECK
and CMIP6 historical simulations, and includes a brief introduction to the
21 CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs.</p></abstract-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation>
Bony, S., Bellon, G., Klocke, D., Sherwood, S., Fermepin, S., and Denvil,
S.: Robust direct effect of carbon dioxide on tropical circulation and
regional precipitation, Nat. Geosci., 6, 447–451, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation>
Bony, S., Stevens, B., Frierson, D. M. W., Jakob, C., Kageyama, M., Pincus,
R., Shepherd, T. G., Sherwood, S. C., Siebesma, A. P., Sobel, A. H.,
Watanabe, M., and Webb, M. J.: Clouds, circulation and climate sensitivity,
Nat. Geosci., 8, 261–268, 2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation>
Brasseur, G. and Carlson, D.: Future directions for the World Climate
Research Programme, Eos, Transactions American Geophysical Union, 96,
<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2015EO033577" target="_blank">doi:10.1029/2015EO033577</a>,
2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation>
CMIP Panel:  WCRP Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP), available
at: <a href="http://www.wcrp-climate.org/index.php/wgcm-cmip/about-cmip" target="_blank">http://www.wcrp-climate.org/index.php/wgcm-cmip/about-cmip</a>, 2016.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation>
Crowley, T. J.: Causes of climate change over the past 1000 years, Science, 289, 270–277, 2000.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation>
Cubasch, U., Wuebbles, D., Chen, D., Facchini, M. C., Frame, D., Mahowald, N., and
Winther, J.-G.: Introduction, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science
Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Stocker, T. F., Qin, D.,
Plattner, G.-K., Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia, Y.,
Bex, V., and Midgley, P. M., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and
New York, NY, USA, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation>
Deser, C., Knutti, R., Solomon, S., and Phillips, A. S.: Communication of the
role of natural variability in future North American climate, Nat. Clim.
Change, 2, 775–779, 2012.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation>
Eyring, V., Righi, M., Lauer, A., Evaldsson, M., Wenzel, S., Jones, C., Anav, A., Andrews, O., Cionni, I., Davin,
E. L., Deser, C., Ehbrecht, C., Friedlingstein, P., Gleckler, P., Gottschaldt, K.-D., Hagemann, S.,
Juckes, M., Kindermann, S., Krasting, J., Kunert, D., Levine, R., Loew, A., Mäkelä, J., Martin, G.,
Mason, E., Phillips, A. S., Read, S., Rio, C., Roehrig, R., Senftleben, D., Sterl, A., van Ulft, L. H., Walton, J., Wang, S., and Williams,
K. D.: ESMValTool (v1.0) – a community diagnostic and performance metrics tool for routine evaluation of
Earth system models in CMIP, Geosci. Model Dev., 9, 1747–1802, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/gmd-9-1747-2016" target="_blank">doi:10.5194/gmd-9-1747-2016</a>, 2016.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation>
Ferraro, R., Waliser, D. E., Gleckler, P., Taylor, K. E., and Eyring, V.:
Evolving obs4MIPs to Support the Sixth Coupled Model Intercomparison Project
(CMIP6), B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-14-00216.1" target="_blank">doi:10.1175/BAMS-D-14-00216.1</a>, online
first,
2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation>
Flato, G., Marotzke, J., Abiodun, B., Braconnot, P., Chou, S. C., Collins,
W., Cox, P., Driouech, F., Emori, S., Eyring, V., Forest, C., Gleckler, P.,
Guilyardi, E., Jakob, C., Kattsov, V., Reason, C., and Rummukainen, M.:
Evaluation of Climate Models, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science
Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Stocker, T. F., Qin,
D., Plattner, G.-K., Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia,
Y., Bex, V., and Midgley, P. M., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK
and New York, NY, USA, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation>
Gates, W. L., Boyle, J. S., Covey, C., Dease, C. G., Doutriaux, C. M., Drach,
R. S., Fiorino, M., Gleckler, P. J., Hnilo, J. J., Marlais, S. M., Phillips,
T. J., Potter, G. L., Santer, B. D., Sperber, K. R., Taylor, K. E., and
Williams, D. N.: An Overview of the Results of the Atmospheric Model
Intercomparison Project (AMIP I), B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 80, 29–55, 1999.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation>
Geoffroy, O., Saint-Martin, D., Olivie, D. J. L., Voldoire, A., Bellon, G.,
and Tyteca, S.: Transient Climate Response in a Two-Layer Energy-Balance
Model. Part I: Analytical Solution and Parameter Calibration Using CMIP5
AOGCM Experiments, J. Climate, 26, 1841–1857, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation>
Gleckler, P. J., Doutriaux, C., Durack P. J., Taylor K. E., Zhang, Y.,
Williams, D. N., Mason, E., and Servonnat, J.: A More Powerful Reality Test
for Climate Models, Eos Trans. AGU, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2016EO051663" target="_blank">doi:10.1029/2016EO051663</a>, 2016.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation>
Gregory, J. and Webb, M.: Tropospheric adjustment induces a cloud component
in CO<sub>2</sub> forcing, J. Climate, 21, 58–71, 2008.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation>
Gregory, J. M.: Long-term effect of volcanic forcing on ocean heat content,
Geophys. Res. Lett., 37, L22701, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2010gl045507" target="_blank">doi:10.1029/2010gl045507</a>, 2010.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation>
Gregory, J. M., Ingram, W. J., Palmer, M. A., Jones, G. S., Stott, P. A.,
Thorpe, R. B., Lowe, J. A., Johns, T. C., and Williams, K. D.: A new method
for diagnosing radiative forcing and climate sensitivity, Geophys. Res.
Lett., 31, L03205, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2003gl018747" target="_blank">doi:10.1029/2003gl018747</a>, 2004.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation>
Gregory, J. M., Bi, D., Collier, M. A., Dix, M. R., Hirst, A. C., Hu, A.,
Huber, M., Knutti, R., Marsland, S. J., Meinshausen, M., Rashid, H. A.,
Rotstayn, L. D., Schurer, A., and Church, J. A.: Climate models without
preindustrial volcanic forcing underestimate historical ocean thermal
expansion, Geophys. Res. Lett., 40, 1600–1604, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation>
Hegerl, G. C., Zwiers, F. W., Braconnot, P., Gillett, N. P., Luo, Y., Marengo
Orsini, J. A., Nicholls, N., Penner, J. E., and Stott, P. A.: Understanding
and Attributing Climate Change, in: Climate Change 2007: The Physical Science
Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fourth Assessment Report of the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, edited by: Solomon, S., Qin, D.,
Manning, M., Chen, Z., Marquis, M., Averyt, K. B., Tignor, M., and Miller, H.
L., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York, NY, USA, 2007.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation>
Houghton, R. A.: How well do we know the flux of CO<sub>2</sub> from land-use
change?, Tellus B, 62, 337–351, 2010.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation>
Hurtt, G. C., Chini, L. P., Frolking, S., Betts, R. A., Feddema, J., Fischer,
G., Fisk, J. P., Hibbard, K., Houghton, R. A., Janetos, A., Jones, C. D.,
Kindermann, G., Kinoshita, T., Goldewijk, K. K., Riahi, K., Shevliakova, E.,
Smith, S., Stehfest, E., Thomson, A., Thornton, P., van Vuuren, D. P., and
Wang, Y. P.: Harmonization of land-use scenarios for the period 1500–2100:
600 years of global gridded annual land-use transitions, wood harvest, and
resulting secondary lands, Climatic Change, 109, 117–161, 2011.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation>
IPCC: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of
Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel
on Climate Change, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York,
NY, USA, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation>
Kamae, Y. and Watanabe, M.: Tropospheric adjustment to increasing CO<sub>2</sub>:
its timescale and the role of land-sea contrast, Clim. Dynam., 41,
3007–3024, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation>
Lawrence, B. N., Balaji, V., Bentley, P., Callaghan, S., DeLuca, C., Denvil,
S., Devine, G., Elkington, M., Ford, R. W., Guilyardi, E., Lautenschlager,
M., Morgan, M., Moine, M.-P., Murphy, S., Pascoe, C., Ramthun, H., Slavin,
P., Steenman-Clark, L., Toussaint, F., Treshansky, A., and Valcke, S.:
Describing Earth system simulations with the Metafor CIM, Geosci. Model Dev.,
5, 1493–1500, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/gmd-5-1493-2012" target="_blank">doi:10.5194/gmd-5-1493-2012</a>, 2012.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation>
Li, C., Stevens, B., and Marotzke, J.: Eurasian winter cooling in the warming
hiatus of 1998–2012, Geophys. Res. Lett., 42, 8131–8139, 2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Boer, G. J., Covey, C., Latif, M., and Stouffer, R. J.:
Intercomparison makes for a better climate model, Eos, Transactions American
Geophysical Union, 78, 445–451, 1997.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Boer, G. J., Covey, C., Latif, M., and Stouffer, R. J.: The
Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP), B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 81,
313–318, 2000.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Covey, C., Taylor, K. E., Delworth, T., Stouffer, R. J., Latif,
M., McAvaney, B., and Mitchell, J. F. B.: THE WCRP CMIP3 Multimodel Dataset:
A New Era in Climate Change Research, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 88, 1383–1394,
2007.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation>
Meehl, G. A., Moss, R., Taylor, K. E., Eyring, V., Stouffer, R. J., Bony, S.,
and Stevens, B.: Climate Model Intercomparisons: Preparing for the Next
Phase, Eos Trans. AGU, 59, 77, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2014EO090001" target="_blank">doi:10.1002/2014EO090001</a>,  2014.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation>
Moss, R. H., Edmonds, J. A., Hibbard, K. A., Manning, M. R., Rose, S. K., van
Vuuren, D. P., Carter, T. R., Emori, S., Kainuma, M., Kram, T., Meehl, G. A.,
Mitchell, J. F. B., Nakicenovic, N., Riahi, K., Smith, S. J., Stouffer, R.
J., Thomson, A. M., Weyant, J. P., and Wilbanks, T. J.: The next generation
of scenarios for climate change research and assessment, Nature, 463,
747–756, 2010.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation>
Murphy, J. M. and Mitchell, J. F. B.: Transient-Response of the Hadley-Center
Coupled Ocean-Atmosphere Model to Increasing Carbon-Dioxide. 2. Spatial and
Temporal Structure of Response, J. Climate, 8, 57–80, 1995.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation>
Myhre, G., Shindell, D., Breìon, F.-M., Collins, W., Fuglestvedt, J.,
Huang, J., Koch, D., Lamarque, J.-F., Lee, D., Mendoza, B., Nakajima, T., Robock, A., Stephens,
G., Takemura, T., and Zhang, H.: Anthropogenic and Natural Radiative
Forcing, in: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of
Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel
on Climate Change, edited by: Stocker, T. F., Qin, D., Plattner, G.-K.,
Tignor, M., Allen, S. K., Boschung, J., Nauels, A., Xia, Y., Bex, V., and
Midgley, P. M., Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK and New York, NY,
USA, 2013.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation>
O'Neill, B. C., Kriegler, E., Ebi, K. L., Kemp-Benedict, E., Riahi, K.,
Rothman, D. S., van Ruijven, B. J., van Vuuren, D. P., Birkmann, J., Kok, K.,
Levy, M., and Solecki, W.: The roads ahead: Narratives for shared
socioeconomic pathways describing world futures in the 21st century, Global
Environ. Chang., <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.01.004" target="_blank">doi:10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.01.004</a>, online first,
2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation>
Phillips, A. S., Deser, C., and Fasullo, J.: Evaluating Modes of Variability
in Climate Models, Eos Trans. AGU, 95, 453–455, 2014.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation>
Rauser, F., Gleckler, P., and Marotzke, J.: Rethinking the Default
Construction of Multimodel Climate Ensembles, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 96,
911–919, 2014.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation>
Sentman, L. T., Shevliakova, E., Stouffer, R. J., and Malyshev, S.: Time
Scales of Terrestrial Carbon Response Related to Land-Use Application:
Implications for Initializing an Earth System Model, Earth Interact., 15,
1–16, 2011.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation>
Sherwood, S. C., Bony, S., Boucher, O., Bretherton, C., Forster, P. M.,
Gregory, J. M., and Stevens, B.: Adjustments in the Forcing-Feedback
Framework for Understanding Climate Change, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 96,
217–228, 2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation>
Stevens, B.: Rethinking the Lower Bound on Aerosol Radiative Forcing, J.
Climate, 28, 4794–4819, 2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation>
Stott, P. A., Mitchell, J. F. B., Allen, M. R., Delworth, T. L., Gregory, J.
M., Meehl, G. A., and Santer, B. D.: Observational constraints on past
attributable warming and predictions of future global warming, J. Climate,
19, 3055–3069, 2006.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation>
Stouffer, R. J., Weaver, A. J., and Eby, M.: A method for obtaining
pre-twentieth century initial conditions for use in climate change studies,
Clim. Dynam., 23, 327–339, 2004.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation>
Stouffer, R. J., Eyring, V., Meehl, G. A., Bony, S., Senior, C., Stevens, B.,
and Taylor, K. E.: CMIP5 Scientific Gaps and Recommendations for CMIP6, B.
Am. Meteorol. Soc., submitted, 2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation>
Taylor, K. E., Stouffer, R. J., and Meehl, G. A.: A Summary of the CMIP5
Experiment Design, available at:
<a href="http://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/docs/Taylor_CMIP5_design.pdf" target="_blank">http://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/docs/Taylor_CMIP5_design.pdf</a> (last access:
13 May 2016), 2009.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation>
Taylor, K. E., Stouffer, R. J., and Meehl, G. A.: An Overview of Cmip5 and
the Experiment Design, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 93, 485–498, 2012.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation>
Teixeira, J., Waliser, D., Ferraro, R., Gleckler, P., Lee, T., and Potter,
G.: Satellite Observations for CMIP5: The Genesis of Obs4MIPs, B. Am.
Meteorol. Soc., 95, 1329–1334, 2014.

</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation>
Trenberth, K. and Asrar, G.: Challenges and Opportunities in Water Cycle
Research: WCRP Contributions, Surv. Geophys., 35, 515–532, 2014.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation>
van Vuuren, D. P., Edmonds, J., Kainuma, M., Riahi, K., Thomson, A., Hibbard,
K., Hurtt, G. C., Kram, T., Krey, V., Lamarque, J. F., Masui, T.,
Meinshausen, M., Nakicenovic, N., Smith, S. J., and Rose, S. K.: The
representative concentration pathways: an overview, Climatic Change, 109,
5–31, 2011.

</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation>
Williams, D. N., Balaji, V., Cinquini, L., Denvil, S., Duffy, D., Evans, B.,
Ferraro, R., Hansen, R., Lautenschlager, M., and Trenham, C.: A Global
Repository for Planet-Sized Experiments and Observations, B. Am. Meteorol.
Soc., <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/bams-d-15-00132.1" target="_blank">doi:10.1175/bams-d-15-00132.1</a>, online first, 2015.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>
<ref-html id="bib1.bib47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation>
Williams, K. and Webb, M.: A quantitative performance assessment of cloud
regimes in climate models, Clim. Dynam., 33, 141–157, 2009.
</mixed-citation></ref-html>--></article>
